<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
    <channel>
        <title>NL-RSE Blog and Events</title>
        <link>https://nl-rse.netlify.app/feed.xml</link>
        <description>NL-RSE Blog feed!</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Thu, 14 Oct 2021 10:24:38 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/nuxt-community/feed-module</generator>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[What Open Science can learn from Free Software]]></title>
            <link>/posts/2021-07-07-JdlC-meetup-June</link>
            <guid>What Open Science can learn from Free Software</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jul 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[
              <p>
                <img
                  alt="Cover image"
                  src="/img/mick-haupt-Spjvmx7MJGs-unsplash.jpg"
                >
              </p>
              <p>Photo by <a href="https://unsplash.com/@rocinante_11?utm_source=unsplash&#x26;utm_medium=referral&#x26;utm_content=creditCopyText">Mick Haupt</a> on <a href="https://unsplash.com/s/photos/wall-garden?utm_source=unsplash&#x26;utm_medium=referral&#x26;utm_content=creditCopyText">Unsplash</a></p>
<p>Authors:<br>
<a href="https://twitter.com/liekedb" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Lieke de Boer</a> / Netherlands eScience Center</p>
<p><a href="https://twitter.com/jdelacueva" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Javier de la Cueva</a> does not like slideshows – "<em>it limits the ways we communicate, like squeezing thoughts into 140 characters</em>", but for the NL-RSE meetup, he made one anyway. De la Cueva is a lawyer, philosopher, and Open Science advocate, with expertise in free software and intellectual property. During the <a href="/events/2021-06-11-meetup.html">meetup on Friday, 11 June 2021</a>, he gave a passionate talk about what the Open Science movement can learn from the Free Software movement, blending the topics of software development and science in a way not unfamiliar to those identifying as RSEs.</p>
<!--break-->
<p>If anyone's an expert on these topics, it's De la Cueva. He switched from Windows to Linux in 2000, after receiving a Blue Screen of Death on his Windows machine – "<em>Why would you create a wall that doesn't allow me to understand something I paid for?</em>". In 2002, when Wikipedia was planning to commercialize, De la Cueva and others <a href="https://www.wired.co.uk/article/wikipedia-spanish-fork" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">forked the Spanish version of the page onto a server in the University of Seville, Spain</a>, proving to Wikipedia's owners that the entire project could be run on non-profit servers – a move some consider responsible for keeping Wikipedia free of commercial ads and paywalls to this day. Later, in 2006, he was, in his own words, "<em>the first lawyer</em> <em>to obtain a judicial ruling where the term <a href="https://copyleft.org/" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank"><em>copyleft</em></a> was included</em>". For the case in question, <a href="https://edri.org/our-work/edrigramnumber4-9spaincc/" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Ladinamo</a>, De la Cueva defended the owners of a bar who were sued for failing to pay the compulsory licensing fee for playing music in their establishment. He won the case by successfully arguing that the music's Creative Commons licenses allowed for public performance, and that no additional fees had to be paid.</p>
<p>In 2014, De la Cueva defended his philosophy thesis, <a href="https://www.researchgate.net/publication/266487696_Pragmaticas_tecnologicas_ciudadanas_y_regeneracion_democratica" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Citizen Technological Pragmatics and Democratic Regeneration</a> (abstract in English, thesis in Spanish). The work discusses how open access, open science, open data, and open government affect public knowledge and democracy. The thesis reflects Javier's varied interests, providing insights from the fields of law, technology, political philosophy, and philosophy of language. Today, De la Cueva works as a lawyer and professor at IE University in Madrid. Along with his university teaching activities, De la Cueva is actively involved in science dissemination, "<em>because a functioning democracy needs its citizens to be informed about scientific development</em>". Science, he says, should not be about <em>who</em> does it, but about <em>what</em> scientists are doing. A common sensical enough statement, but one that may sound like an unrealistic utopia to anyone who has ever worked in academia.</p>
<p>American sociologist of science <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_K._Merton#Sociology_of_science_and_CUDOS" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Robert K. Merton</a> recognized this tension: he observed that the social system of science works both in agreement with, but also often in contradiction to, its own ideal. Merton expressed the ideal of science in four concrete moral principles, referred to as <strong>CUDOS</strong> : Science must be <strong>C</strong>ommunist (in the sense of communal), meaning that all scientists have common ownership of scientific goods, giving up intellectual property of their work in exchange for recognition. It should be <strong>U</strong>niversal, or independent of the socio-political status and personal attributes of its participants. Scientific institutions should also be <strong>D</strong>isinterested, meaning personal gain of individuals within them is inferior to the greater goal of the scientific enterprise. Lastly, science must have <strong>O</strong>rganised <strong>S</strong>cepticism.</p>
<p>For science to be in line with CUDOS, we have to rethink the relationship between scientists and their work. Because every scientific institution inevitably brings their own view of the world to the way they collect, analyse, and publish their data, open access to scientific publications only is not enough. After all, after data is collected, it is translated and analysed (often with the use of in-house developed software), written up into results, preprints and research papers, which can obscure the bias inherent in every step of the way leading up to that publication. Ideally, science openly shares every output that it creates, including data, publications, education, software and other tools. These outputs should be reused to two ends: First, to reproduce existing findings, De la Cueva argues – "<em>there is too much emphasis on novelty in science</em>". Second, to combine all levels of existing scientific outputs into new structures, which De la Cueva considers crucial for innovation.</p>
<p>Open Science can look at the Free Software movement for an example on how to openly share its output. Free Software developers recognise the importance of their software's reusability, which means they understand the importance of licensing and diversity of licenses. Scientists, on the other hand, do not hold the power to put a license on their scientific output. De la Cueva argues that this should change. Science could, for example, take inspiration from the Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF), which manages standards for the Internet. Any contributor permits the IETF to distribute their contributions freely, and in turn can use any of the other standards, which have been licensed in the same way. This results in an open Internet that is freely accessible to all. If we want CUDOS for science, the same mechanism could be applied to scientific outputs, where scientists permit their contributions to be distributed freely, and in turn are able to freely use others' contributions.</p>
<p>De la Cueva points at two signs that science is moving in the right direction. First, the existence of preprint servers. Second, the <a href="https://www.aje.com/arc/open-access-changing-landscape/" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">rise in peer-reviewed open access journals</a>. And arguably, the increasingly common practice of publicly sharing research software, and adherence to FAIR data principles, can be counted as positive signs too. But there's still work to be done: "<em>We still pay 9500 euros to obtain open access in</em> Nature. <em>And the default for publications is still</em> All rights reserved. <em>This has to end.</em>"</p>
<p>We'd like to thank Javier de la Cueva for his talk on Open Science. This talk was part of the June NL-RSE meetup. NL-RSE meetups are monthly events, where those working on the intersection between research and software development (from PhD students to Scientific Programmers) at Dutch institutes come together to discuss relevant topics. Our next <a href="/events/2021-09-15-meetup.html">NL-RSE meetup is on September 16</a> and will cover reproducible research articles. Speakers include <a href="https://twitter.com/fperez_org?lang=en" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Fernando Pérez</a>, creator of the IPython programming environment, <a href="https://twitter.com/GiuliaGuizza" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Giulia Guizzardi</a>, Innovation Officer at eLife, and <a href="https://twitter.com/adinakrik?lang=en" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Adina Wagner</a>, author of the software package Datalad. <a href="https://nl-rse.org/events/2021-09-15-meetup.html" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">More information and sign-up here</a>.</p>
<p>Lieke de Boer</p>
<p>Thanks to Lourens Veen and Pablo Rodríguez-Sánchez for helpful comments and additions.</p>
            ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[A demo in the life of an RSE]]></title>
            <link>/posts/2021-06-16-meetup-april</link>
            <guid>A demo in the life of an RSE</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 16 Jun 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[
              <p>
                <img
                  alt="Cover image"
                  src="/img/shane-aldendorff-mQHEgroKw2k-unsplash.jpg"
                >
              </p>
              <p><em>Photo by <a href="https://unsplash.com/@pluyar?utm_source=unsplash&#x26;utm_medium=referral&#x26;utm_content=creditCopyText">Shane Aldendorff</a> on <a href="https://unsplash.com/s/photos/mechanism?utm_source=unsplash&#x26;utm_medium=referral&#x26;utm_content=creditCopyText">Unsplash</a></em></p>
<p>Authors:<br>
<a href="https://twitter.com/liekedb" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Lieke de Boer</a> / Netherlands eScience Center</p>
<p>If you’re curious about the kinds of things a Research Software Engineer (RSE) can get done when employed in that capacity, you’d have enjoyed the April 2021 NL-RSE meetup, where we saw the demos of two RSE software projects. <a href="https://rse.diagnijmegen.nl/members/paul-konstantin-gerke/" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Paul Konstantin Gerke</a>, RSE from the diagnostic imaging analysis group (DIAG) at Radboud UMC, gave a demo of the <a href="grand-challenge.org">Grand Challenge</a>. The Grand Challenge is a Python-based platform where researchers and engineers can annotate and analyze medical images to, for example, judge the likelihood that a patient has a COVID-19 infection, based on a CT scan of that patient’s lungs. The platform also allows users to compare their own medical imaging machine learning algorithms to those of others. The Grand Challenge website lists different leaderboards for several “challenges”, or medical imaging machine learning problems, and ranks the performance of competing algorithms for each challenge.</p>
<p><a href="http://uva-aias.net/en/staff/casper-kaandorp" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Casper Kaandorp</a>, RSE from Utrecht University, presented the second demo: NIDM (Networking during Infectious Disease Model). NIDM is an Elixir web application that can be used for running social experiments. Casper demonstrated a social risk-taking behavioral experiment, which consisted of the simulation of an infectious disease spreading through a social network. Study participants are supposed to earn money by befriending others in their network, while minimizing connections with infected individuals. Believe it or not, the app was conceptualized before the COVID-19 pandemic.</p>
<p>The demos were followed by a panel, where the meeting chair Carlos Martinez-Ortiz asked the two RSEs how their respective RSE groups are set up, and what challenges they have faced. Below is a summary of their conversation.  <!--break--></p>
<h3 id="how-is-your-rse-group-set-up"><a href="#how-is-your-rse-group-set-up" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"><span class="icon icon-link"></span></a>How is your RSE group set up?</h3>
<p><strong>Paul:</strong> My group is part of the DIAG: the research arm of the Radboud UMC radiology department. The DIAG consists of about 60 people, split up into teams of 5-10 people with different research specialities. The RSE group is one such team. Our RSEs take on work that can address common goals between multiple DIAG research teams. The research team leaders establish common goals in a panel, and the RSE group tries to implement software features in line with the goals communicated by the panel. This is how the RSE group has built the Grand Challenge, a platform that can be useful for all research teams.</p>
<p><strong>Casper:</strong> I am part of a group of RSEs that is helping researchers from all backgrounds at the Utrecht University with different kinds of problems, so our approach is broader than what Paul describes. The range of projects we work on is immense, from easy projects like setting up a GitHub repository, to helping people with machine learning projects that are extremely complex.</p>
<h3 id="what-kind-of-resources-does-your-rse-group-have-and-is-that-enough"><a href="#what-kind-of-resources-does-your-rse-group-have-and-is-that-enough" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"><span class="icon icon-link"></span></a>What kind of resources does your RSE group have, and is that enough?</h3>
<p><strong>Casper:</strong> At the moment, funding is not a problem for our team of 10 people. There’s a cap on how many people can work in our group, though. Our team grew in the past months, so our capacity is currently increasing, but we can’t take on new projects too fast, because we never know what kind of project may come to us. Any kind of task can come up, which makes the job interesting, but also unpredictable, and can leave us overwhelmed with work.</p>
<p><strong>Paul:</strong> Our RSE group is facilitating research funded by NWO. To add features to the platform, we should be fulfilling researcher needs, and working in line with the available funding. There is also another funding stream however: there are industry partners (AWS for example, for cloud expenses) that provide resources. But we also develop and market medical products, which brings in money. </p>
<h3 id="is-there-a-limit-on-time-and-budget-that-you-spend-on-different-projects"><a href="#is-there-a-limit-on-time-and-budget-that-you-spend-on-different-projects" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"><span class="icon icon-link"></span></a>Is there a limit on time and budget that you spend on different projects?</h3>
<p><strong>Paul:</strong> We want attach deadlines to feature development, because ever-ongoing projects can be a problem. When you’re given one year to finish a project, that project will be on the backburner, and can forever be pushed back. The time and money we spend on features is determined by what our stakeholders want, and what the panel decides we should work on. For example, a stakeholder may want our software to include Magnetic Resonance (MR) support. We then decide that in order to provide that, we need to implement feature A, B and C. We bring our proposal for feature A, B and C back to the panel, who may tell us to focus on feature A. Then we like to commit a set amount of time to developing feature A.</p>
<p><strong>Casper:</strong> At UU, our coordinator tries to put a minimum of 2 people on each project, so no one works alone. Sometimes it is unavoidable for someone to work alone on a project, though. This can be an issue, but when you are with so few people and such a variety of projects, it’s sometimes impossible to structure it differently. We used to have an undefined amount of time for any given project, which often meant that projects would take more than half a year to get done. We now have a rule that a project should be finished within half a year of one person’s full time amount of work. A common challenge we still face is that we may start working on a project, but the researcher who approached us becomes busy with something else, and the project is left for some time. The researcher sometimes comes back and expects the RSEs to pick up where they left off, which is then often impossible. </p>
<h3 id="what-kind-of-projects-do-researchers-approach-you-with"><a href="#what-kind-of-projects-do-researchers-approach-you-with" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"><span class="icon icon-link"></span></a>What kind of projects do researchers approach you with? </h3>
<p><strong>Casper:</strong> We get requests from every kind of researcher there is. Half of those requests lead to nothing, because the researcher isn’t ready yet. A quarter is consultancy and includes helping researchers with questions about how to set up a job on Lisa (HPC system at Utrecht University). These are the type of questions that can be solved in a few days.</p>
<p>The last 25% is wild. It can be anything. Recently, there was a researcher who went to the Congo and recorded two types of audio. One of jungle sounds, in the wild, and another of sounds from a monkey sanctuary. They then came to us with the question if it would be possible to create an algorithm that could predict biodiversity in each surrounding based on these recordings. So we helped them to do this.</p>
<p>I also worked on a project that looked at betting behaviour in sports bets, which is similar in some ways to betting in the context of the stock market. The application we developed browsed bookmaking websites to get a feeling for betting odds in sports matches. The application would bet very heavily on one contestant when the odds were 50/50. The goal of this was to try and see if the application could “swing the market”, so other participants would follow the application’s lead. Eventually, there was a very small significant effect of our betting, meaning that people did follow the application’s bets. I was hoping we’d make some money with it, because during the first two months we won quite a lot! Unfortunately, we lost a lot later on. It was a really interesting project, but not a profitable one. </p>
<p><strong>Paul:</strong> The work we do at the DIAG may look very focused, but that was the RSE trick: We stripped all the focus away, and ended up with a generic solution for different fields. We don’t tackle the very specific things anymore. What Casper says is right; with a lot of different projects, it’s easy to get completely overwhelmed and not finish things. This is where our structure really helped us out. </p>
<h3 id="whats-staffing-and-managing-an-rse-group-like-how-do-you-find-the-right-person-to-hire-and-how-do-you-convince-funders-to-keep-funding-you"><a href="#whats-staffing-and-managing-an-rse-group-like-how-do-you-find-the-right-person-to-hire-and-how-do-you-convince-funders-to-keep-funding-you" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"><span class="icon icon-link"></span></a>What’s staffing and managing an RSE group like? How do you find the right person to hire, and how do you convince funders to keep funding you?</h3>
<p><strong>Paul:</strong> It’s definitely untreaded territory. Recently our group grew a lot, to 11 RSEs in total. We’re still learning how to manage such a team. It can be quite difficult to find the right employees. We’re in the East of the Netherlands, and as a hospital, you compete with industry for software engineers who have the skills that you need. It’s common that those candidates move to the Randstad if they get a good offer there.  On top of that, operating from a hospital has its own challenges. Hospitals are not really known for building software - they’re geared to patient care, and maybe research, but not software development.</p>
<p>Our future strategy will be to work more as a remote team. We now have had one year of practicing working remotely of course, because of the circumstances in the COVID-19 pandemic. And there are many benefits to RSEs who work with us. The work is meaningful, challenging and interesting, and the hospital is a flexible workplace.</p>
<h3 id="closing-remarks"><a href="#closing-remarks" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"><span class="icon icon-link"></span></a>Closing remarks</h3>
<p>Thanks to Casper and Paul for participating in this panel and for sharing their diverse experiences being part of RSE groups.</p>
<p>Are you an RSE working in a group? Is the structure of your group different from what is described here? We would love to hear your experiences!</p>
            ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[What is really needed for software reusability?]]></title>
            <link>/posts/2021-04-21-software reusability</link>
            <guid>What is really needed for software reusability?</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 02 Apr 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[
              <p>
                <img
                  alt="Cover image"
                  src="/img/maria-shanina-dWHeuGw0fBM-unsplash.jpg"
                >
              </p>
              <p><em>Photo by <a href="https://unsplash.com/@mariashanina?utm_source=unsplash&#x26;utm_medium=referral&#x26;utm_content=creditCopyText">Maria Shanina</a> on <a href="https://unsplash.com/?utm_source=unsplash&#x26;utm_medium=referral&#x26;utm_content=creditCopyText">Unsplash</a></em></p>
<p>Authors:<br>
<a href="https://twitter.com/fdiblen" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Faruk Diblen</a> / Netherlands eScience Center<br>
<a href="https://twitter.com/barbaravreede" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Barbara Vreede</a> / Netherlands eScience Center<br>
<a href="https://twitter.com/dgawehns" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Daniela Gawehns</a> / Leiden University<br>
<a href="https://twitter.com/neocarlitos" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Carlos Martinez</a> / Netherlands eScience Center</p>
<p>Writing software has become one of the most important parts of the research process. In its simplest form, research software is a single script that can, for example, be used for collecting, processing and/or visualising data. Complex analyses and workflows are consolidated into larger pieces of software that are often the result of research and the subject of papers. The increasing importance of computer code in research is highlighted by the growing level of attention to software from the European Open Science Cloud<sup id="fnref-sirs"><a href="#fn-sirs" class="footnote-ref">SIRS</a></sup> and the OECD Recommendation on Access to Research Data which now includes software<sup id="fnref-oecd"><a href="#fn-oecd" class="footnote-ref">OECD</a></sup>.</p>
<!--break-->
<p>One of the missions of the Netherlands eScience Center is promoting software reuse. In order to improve research software reusability, the Center’s Software Sustainability SIG (Special Interest Group) compiled a reusability checklist for research software (see Table 1). The checklist is meant as a minimum list of requirements that one would expect to see (as a user) in order to be able to use a given piece of software (whether it is a library, or a single script). The checklist covers aspects such as documentation and licensing.</p>
<p><strong>Note</strong>: reusability can be easily confused with another important term: reproducibility. The two are closely related, but not quite the same: the former is an important component of the latter, but software need not be reusable to be reproducible. Roughly speaking and for the purpose of this blog: we talk about reproducibility when the same code and same data are used to produce the same results; we talk about reusability when the same code is used with different data to produce new results (read <a href="https://github.com/NLeSC/guide/discussions/237" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">detailed discussion</a>). The software reusability checklist is aimed primarily at reuse, but it may also be applicable to ensure reproducibility of scientific results produced by the use of software.</p>
<hr>
<p>The following is the set of minimum requirements we defined for code to be <strong>repeatable</strong>, <strong>re-runnable</strong> and <strong>portable</strong><sup id="fnref-reproducibility"><a href="#fn-reproducibility" class="footnote-ref">reproducibility</a></sup>:</p>
<p><strong>The software</strong>:</p>
<ul>
<li>is in an accessible repository, preferably version controlled;</li>
<li>has a license (see: ‘The license’);</li>
<li>is documented (see: ‘The documentation’).</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>The license</strong>:</p>
<ul>
<li>allows for reuse;</li>
<li>is compatible with the dependencies’ licenses.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>The documentation</strong>:</p>
<ul>
<li>has installation instructions, including good descriptions of:
<ul>
<li>the hardware it depends on (e.g. GPUs);</li>
<li>the operating system the software has been tested on;</li>
<li>software requirements (libraries, shell settings, etc).</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>explains usage, specifying:
<ul>
<li>what the software does;</li>
<li>how it can be used;</li>
<li>what options/parameters are available.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>contains examples of how to run it.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Finally</strong>:</p>
<ul>
<li>If the software depends on any sort of data, the data should be available</li>
</ul>
<hr>
<p>Table 1. Minimum requirements list for software reusability</p>
<hr>
<h3 id="escience-center-reusabilithon"><a href="#escience-center-reusabilithon" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"><span class="icon icon-link"></span></a>eScience Center Reusabilithon</h3>
<p>We had initially planned to hold the Reusabilithon with a relatively large group of eScience engineers, as part of our internal activities. However, with the lockdown affecting our capacity early 2021, we changed our plan. Instead of canceling the event, we decided to carry out the event online, and on a small scale. As a bonus, this helped against the lockdown-induced boredom, by breaking the routine and spending some time doing something interesting and fun!</p>
<p>Two eScience Center RSEs worked together via Teams for one afternoon. They applied this list to 3 different pieces of software (<a href="https://www.research-software.nl/software/sv-callers" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">sv-callers</a>, <a href="https://github.com/multiscale/muscle3" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">muscle3</a> &#x26; <a href="https://github.com/DeepRank/iScore" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">iScore</a>) developed in-house. The following are the observations by the engineers in this small reusabilaton:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>It took us about 1 hour per use case working together, and most time was spent getting the example to work. Independently from how each tool did, we found that the minimum requirements list is fit for purpose – no points in the list felt to us as if they should be left out; we also did not feel that there was something missing in this list.</p>
<p>One point which we did find challenging: it is not easy to determine at a glance if there are any conflicts with the dependencies of the software. It could be helpful to have a check or remark that dependencies have compatible licenses</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This experience describes an encouraging first experiment. However, it was conducted on a very small scale, and by engineers who were vaguely familiar with the software in question.</p>
<p>As a follow up, a discussion session during the <a href="https://nl-rse.org/events/2021-02-11-meetup.html#software-re-usability--what-is-needed" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">NL-RSE meetup</a> led to the writing of this blog post. The Software Sustainability SIG would like to organise a larger <em>reusabilithon</em> with participants from a broader audience and from a wider range of organisations; very similar in format and spirit to the already successful <a href="https://reprohack.github.io/reprohack-hq/" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Reprohack</a>. However, where the latter focuses on the <em>reproducibility</em> of research results, during a reusabilithon participants and aim for reusability. As explained earlier in this post, we understand <em>reusability</em> to be using existing code on new data (even if such data is just parameters).</p>
<p>One of the aims of a future <em>reusabilithon</em> is to gather more feedback on the suitability of the current reusability checklist and improve it. The long-term aim of such a list is to provide researchers with a useful tool to be able to improve the reusability of the software they produce.</p>
<p>The long term aim of running a <em>reusabilithon</em> is making RSE's (and researchers writing research code) aware of what reusability is about and to develop their expertise in using tools to improve reusability. In the future, some of the checks in the reusability checklist could be automated by using tools such as <a href="https://github.com/fair-software/howfairis" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">howfairis</a>, <a href="https://github.com/fair-software/fairtally" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">fairtally</a>, <a href="https://fossa.com/product/open-source-license-compliance" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">fossa open source compliance management</a>, <a href="https://www.augurlabs.io/live-examples/" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Augur</a>, <a href="https://gitext.gfz-potsdam.de/software/services/fair/software-quality-assurance" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">GFZ software quality assurance</a>, etc. We expect the reusabilithon can help identify additional tools that can automate some checks. However instead of automating everything from the start, we need to validate that the points in this checklist are indeed useful for software reuse.</p>
<h3 id="are-you-interested-in-participating-in-future-reusabilithons-contact-us"><a href="#are-you-interested-in-participating-in-future-reusabilithons-contact-us" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"><span class="icon icon-link"></span></a>Are you interested in participating in future reusabilithons? Contact us!</h3>
<p>Dear reader, if you are involved in developing research software -- whether it is in the form of small data analysis scripts or complex libraries -- and you would like to participate in future reusabilithons, please leave a comment or send an email to <a href="mailto:c.martinez@esciencecenter.nl">c.martinez@esciencecenter.nl</a>, and join our effort!</p>
<h3 id="references"><a href="#references" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"><span class="icon icon-link"></span></a>References</h3>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn-sirs">E. C. D. G. for Research and Innovation., Scholarly infrastructures for research software: report from the EOSC Executive Board Working Group (WG) Architecture Task Force (TF) SIRS. LU: Publications Office, 2020. <a href="https://data.europa.eu/doi/10.2777/28598" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">https://data.europa.eu/doi/10.2777/28598</a><a href="#fnref-sirs" class="footnote-backref">↩</a></li>
<li id="fn-oecd">Alan Paic, Making data for science as open as possible to address global challenges <a href="https://oecd-innovation-blog.com/2021/01/20/oecd-recommendation-access-research-data-public-funding-update-covid-19/" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">https://oecd-innovation-blog.com/2021/01/20/oecd-recommendation-access-research-data-public-funding-update-covid-19/</a><a href="#fnref-oecd" class="footnote-backref">↩</a></li>
<li id="fn-reproducibility">J. Freire and F. Chirigati (2018) Provenance and the Different Flavors of Computational Reproducibility. Bulletin of the IEEE Computer Society Technical Committee on Data Engineering, Vol 41, no. 1, p.15-26 <a href="http://sites.computer.org/debull/A18mar/A18MAR-CD.pdf#page=17" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">http://sites.computer.org/debull/A18mar/A18MAR-CD.pdf#page=17</a><a href="#fnref-reproducibility" class="footnote-backref">↩</a></li>
</ol>
</div>
            ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[How to make research software a first-class citizen in the Netherlands?]]></title>
            <link>/posts/2020-09-22-RS-first-class-citizen</link>
            <guid>How to make research software a first-class citizen in the Netherlands?</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 22 Sep 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[
              <p>
                <img
                  alt="Cover image"
                  src="/img/Class_159_First_Class_Seating.jpg"
                >
              </p>
              <p><em>Image credit: <a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Class_159_First_Class_Seating.jpg" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Clive Warneford</a> / <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.0" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">CC BY-SA</a></em></p>
<p>TL;DR -- Read <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4015242" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">our recommendations</a> to make research software a first-class citizen.</p>
<!--break-->
<p><em>This blog post is also posted <a href="https://openworking.wordpress.com/2020/09/23/how-to-make-research-software-a-first-class-citizen-in-the-netherlands/" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">here</a> and [here](: <a href="https://dans.knaw.nl/en/current/news/201craising-the-profile-of-research-software201d-2013-a-new-position-paper-contributing-to-open-science" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">https://dans.knaw.nl/en/current/news/201craising-the-profile-of-research-software201d-2013-a-new-position-paper-contributing-to-open-science</a>).</em></p>
<p>Antoni van Leeuwenhoek is considered the father of microbiology. His discovery of microbes, using the lenses he made himself, created an entire new field of research. He was at the same time a researcher and a tool maker: his research would have not been possible without the tools he built. Leeuwenhoek was well known for both his discoveries in microbiology as well as the unmatched quality of his lenses.</p>
<p>Four centuries after Leeuwenhoek, research tools have only gained importance. Recently, a new type of tool gained critical importance: research software. The 2020 COVID-19 pandemic has brought up to the public eye how <a href="https://www.software.ac.uk/blog/2020-05-07-better-software-better-covid-19-research" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">important research software is</a>.</p>
<p>However, research software does not receive the recognition it deserves. A group of members of the <a href="http://nl-rse.org/" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">NL-RSE network</a>, and software minded data specialists, got together in an attempt to raise the profile of research software. <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4015242" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Our position paper</a> provides further details.</p>
<p>Back in March 2019, we had a <a href="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.2647436" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">meeting with NWO</a> about the role of software in research. Following that meeting, we wrote a <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.3378571" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">position paper</a> with recommendations for funding agencies and research institutions to raise the profile of research software. In August 2019 made it publicly available for <a href="https://nl-rse.org/2019/09/17/RaisingResearchSoftware.html" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">comments from the RSE community</a>. In November 2019, we also had a <a href="https://nl-rse.org/events/NL-RSE19.html" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">feedback session during the NL-RSE conference</a>. The author group got together again in January 2020 to integrate the community feedback. After a long revision process, the <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4015242" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">“final” version</a> is ready. This paper focuses on the Netherlands, but the issues and recommendations could be adapted and adopted by other countries.</p>
<p>These recommendations have been broadly commented on however if you would like to comment on them feel free to reach out to any of the authors or contact us via the <a href="https://nl-rse.org/pages/communication.html" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">NL-RSE network</a>.</p>
            ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Looking back at NL-RSE19]]></title>
            <link>/posts/2019-12-02-Looking-back-at-NL-RSE19</link>
            <guid>Looking back at NL-RSE19</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 02 Dec 2019 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[
              <p>
                <img
                  alt="Cover image"
                  src="/img/nl-rse19/niels.jpg"
                >
              </p>
              <p>Ben van Werkhoven and Niels Drost (Netherlands eScience Center, NL-RSE)</p>
<p>The first RSE conference in the Netherlands was held Wednesday 20 November 2019 at the Johan Cruijff Arena Amsterdam!</p>
<!--break-->
<p>Ben van Werkhoven opened the conference and introduced our first speaker, Niels Drost, member of the NL-RSE core team.</p>
<p>Niels gave a brief status update of NL-RSE and some announcements. Niels explained how important it is to have an RSE conference. As part of this academic career Niels has visited many computer science and domain science conferences, but when visiting the first RSE Conference in the UK in 2016, he suddenly realized that this conference was the first that he had ever attended that was actually organized for him!</p>
<p>Back at home, Niels wasted no time and started forming a group of people to found NL-RSE, which finally happened in April 2017. Today, NL-RSE represents 179 Research Software Engineers from over 35 different organizations in the Netherlands.</p>
<p>To keep NL-RSE going, we need more volunteers to join the core team! The core team is responsible for all of the organization of NL-RSE and organizing events like the NL-RSE19 conference. Please send an email to <a href="mailto:info@nl-rse.org">info@nl-rse.org</a> if you’re interested in joining the core team.</p>
<p>Tania Allard, RSE in scientific computing and machine learning at Microsoft, RSE Society trustee, and diversity chair at the UK-RSE conference this year, gave the keynote presentation titled “IMPLICIT NONE: Intentional inclusion and diversity in the RSE movement”.</p>
<p><img alt="Tania Allard - Implicit none: intentional inclusion and diversity in the RSE movement" src="/img/nl-rse19/tania-title-slide.png"></p>
<p>Tania started by explaining that the RSE movement takes the broadest possible definition of the Research Software Engineer. Anyone who identifies as such can consider themselves an RSE, whether you are a researcher who codes, a developer who conducts research, or someone who studies research software.</p>
<p>Tania also explained that, in general, the role of the RSE within academia is much broader than a researcher who codes or a coder who researches. In addition to developing software, RSEs build communities, manage projects, innovate, teach and mentor others, manage data sets, and conduct research, but they are sometimes also activists, and outcasts within the academic landscape. In general, there are many more people important to academia than the subset of people that are considered Academics.</p>
<p>It does not matter where you are on the spectrum between software engineering and research. Ever since the RSE movement started, there has been the opportunity for people to self-describe as RSEs. The International RSE community promotes inclusiveness and values diversity.</p>
<p>After the keynote, we broke off into parallel sessions, featuring many different talks with a nice balance between RSE community and technology-focused contributions. See <a href="/events/NL-RSE19.html">the NL-RSE19 event page</a> for the program and slides of most presentations.</p>
<h2 id="comments-from-the-participants"><a href="#comments-from-the-participants" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"><span class="icon icon-link"></span></a>Comments from the participants</h2>
<p>During the day, many lively discussions took place. Most live, some online.</p>
<!---- [TWITTER MENTIONS]  ---->
<blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">Keynote by <a href="https://twitter.com/ixek?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@ixek</a>, arguing that <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/RSE?src=hash&#x26;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">#RSE</a> is a multi-hyphen profession <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/NL_RSE19?src=hash&#x26;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">#NL_RSE19</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/nl_rse?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@nl_rse</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/eScienceCenter?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@eScienceCenter</a> <a href="https://t.co/0q97Sbr8jd">pic.twitter.com/0q97Sbr8jd</a></p>— Florian Huber (@me_datapoint) <a href="https://twitter.com/me_datapoint/status/1197080239094018049?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">November 20, 2019</a></blockquote> <script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">📢📢 all with me: those who develop research software and collect/manage/archive data deserve recognition!!! <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/NL_RSE?src=hash&#x26;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">#NL_RSE</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/nl_rse?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@nl_rse</a> <a href="https://t.co/IiwzvJIyMs">pic.twitter.com/IiwzvJIyMs</a></p>— ✨𝕋𝕒𝕟𝕚𝕒 💀🇲🇽 🇬🇧 she/her (@ixek) <a href="https://twitter.com/ixek/status/1197089358324486144?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">November 20, 2019</a></blockquote> <script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">So proud to present our results on comparing solutions to collect historical tweets in <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/NL_RSE19?src=hash&#x26;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">#NL_RSE19</a> <a href="https://t.co/GiHzTDQnFN">pic.twitter.com/GiHzTDQnFN</a></p>— Parisa Zahedi (@parisaZahedi) <a href="https://twitter.com/parisaZahedi/status/1197864354051432448?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">November 22, 2019</a></blockquote> <script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">Getting first users: the do's and dont's by Gerasimos Chourdakis <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/NL_RSE19?src=hash&#x26;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">#NL_RSE19</a> <a href="https://t.co/pv7uQBYtRK">pic.twitter.com/pv7uQBYtRK</a></p>— Albert Meroño (@albertmeronyo) <a href="https://twitter.com/albertmeronyo/status/1197107091791601664?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">November 20, 2019</a></blockquote> <script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">Brilliant talk + demo about open science and literate programming by <a href="https://twitter.com/jhidding?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@jhidding</a>. Nice to find people sharing my interests/obsessions at <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/NL_RSE19?src=hash&#x26;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">#NL_RSE19</a><br><br>cc <a href="https://twitter.com/jdelacueva?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@jdelacueva</a> <a href="https://t.co/QNq9TpxuUA">pic.twitter.com/QNq9TpxuUA</a></p>— Pablo Rodríguez (@DonMostrenco) <a href="https://twitter.com/DonMostrenco/status/1197108851306356736?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">November 20, 2019</a></blockquote> <script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">Really glad to have attended <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/NL_RSE19?src=hash&#x26;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">#NL_RSE19</a>. Here's our report from the event: <a href="https://t.co/Q1f25mOh8L">https://t.co/Q1f25mOh8L</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/RSEng?src=hash&#x26;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">#RSEng</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/nl_rse?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@nl_rse</a></p>— RSE at Imperial College (@ImperialRSE) <a href="https://twitter.com/ImperialRSE/status/1197829788817412101?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">November 22, 2019</a></blockquote> <script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<h2 id="thanks"><a href="#thanks" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"><span class="icon icon-link"></span></a>Thanks!</h2>
<p>We would like to thank everyone who helped in organizing the conference, in particular Sacha van Breugel, and Carlos Martinez Ortiz and Mateusz Kuzak who unfortunately couldn’t be there, as well as all the volunteers that helped out during the day!</p>
<h2 id="outlook-for-nl-rse-2020"><a href="#outlook-for-nl-rse-2020" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"><span class="icon icon-link"></span></a>Outlook for NL-RSE 2020</h2>
<p>After a successful conference, it makes sense to look ahead to next year’s conference and the period that lies in between. Next year, we hope to further grow the NL-RSE community, find more volunteers to join the core team, organize another conference (NL-RSE20), and create a more formal organization for NL-RSE! If you’re interested in helping us make this happen, please let us know at <a href="mailto:info@nl-rse.org">info@nl-rse.org</a>!</p>
            ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[FAIR Software at the 2019 eScience Symposium]]></title>
            <link>/posts/2019-11-29-FAIR-Software-eScience2019</link>
            <guid>FAIR Software at the 2019 eScience Symposium</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 29 Nov 2019 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[
              <p>
                <img
                  alt="Cover image"
                  src="/img/fair-software-escience/banner.jpg"
                >
              </p>
              <p>Ben van Werkhoven (Netherlands eScience Center, NL-RSE)
James Meakin (Radboud UMC, NL-RSE)
Anna-Lena Lamprecht (Utrecht University)
Stephan Druskat (DLR, Humboldt Universität zu Berlin)
Pablo Rodriguez-Sanchez (Netherlands eScience Center)</p>
<p>FAIR data has been on everybody’s lips for a while. Many think that FAIR software will become “the next big thing” in eScience. Reasons enough to devote a session at the National eScience Symposium to the discussion of FAIR and its meaning for research software.</p>
<!--break-->
<p>James Meakin from Radboud UMC and NL-RSE started by introducing the topic for the session. The <a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/sdata.2016.18" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">FAIR Guiding Principles</a> were defined in 2016 for scientific data management and stewardship, aiming to improve the Findability, Accessibility, Interoperability, and Reusability of research data. Given that software is key to modern science, research software should also be FAIR. How can the FAIR principles be applied to software? What should they be? What challenges exist? How do we get there?</p>
<p>The session featured three talks and a panel discussion, with the session’s speakers as panel members. We used the mentimeter Q&#x26;A feature to allow the audience to submit and vote on questions and discussion points for the panel discussion at the end of the session.</p>
<h2 id="anna-lena-lamprecht-towards-fair-principles-for-research-software"><a href="#anna-lena-lamprecht-towards-fair-principles-for-research-software" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"><span class="icon icon-link"></span></a>Anna-Lena Lamprecht: Towards FAIR principles for Research Software</h2>
<p><img alt="Anna-Lena Lamprecht: Towards FAIR principles for Research Software" src="/img/fair-software-escience/anna-lena.jpg"></p>
<p>Anna-Lena Lamprecht, assistant professor of Software Technology at Utrecht University, presented the main findings from the paper <a href="https://doi.org/10.3233/DS-190026" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">“Towards FAIR principles for research software”</a> that she recently published together with several co-authors from the European eScience community: Software and data share some properties, but they are not the same and hence a differentiated interpretation of the FAIR principles is required. For example, one point of ongoing discussion is whether the FAIR principles, which do not demand data to be open, should require software to be open source. Another much-debated relationship has been the one between FAIR and software quality, naturally of great concern in the RSE community. Here it helps to distinguish between form and function of software. FAIR can help to ensure quality of the form of software, but the quality of the functionality of the software goes beyond what FAIR intends to cover.</p>
<p>After these general considerations, Anna-Lena continued with the proposal for FAIR Guiding Principles for software, taking the FAIR data principles as a starting point. Many of the proposed changes are effectively a rephrasing by replacing “(meta)data” with “software and its associated metadata”. Other changes extend or reinterpret the FAIR data principles because software, in contrast to data, is of composite nature, needs to deal with dependencies and evolve along with the changing eScience ecosystems, and hence often comes in different versions.</p>
<p>Perhaps the biggest change from the FAIR data principles is in the following principle (a reinterpretation and extension of the original interoperability principle I2):</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“Software use and produce data in types and formats that are formally described using controlled vocabularies that follow the FAIR principles.”</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This is remarkable because it requires FAIR software to only work with FAIR data, whereas FAIR data does not require to have been produced by only FAIR software.</p>
<p>Anna-Lena’s slides are available <a href="https://www.slideshare.net/annalenalamprecht/towards-fair-principles-for-research-software/" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">here</a>.</p>
<h2 id="stephan-druskat-dare-to-be-mair-than-just-fair"><a href="#stephan-druskat-dare-to-be-mair-than-just-fair" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"><span class="icon icon-link"></span></a>Stephan Druskat: Dare to be mair than just FAIR!</h2>
<p><img alt="Stephan Druskat: Dare to be mair than just FAIR!" src="/img/fair-software-escience/stephan.jpg"></p>
<p>Stephan Druskat is an RSE working in linguistics, and researching software sustainability with a focus on software citation. With his talk titled “Dare to be mair than just FAIR!” Stephan challenged us to think beyond only the FAIR principles.</p>
<p>Of course, making digital objects FAIR is a great step in the right direction for research. FAIR enables easier, better, and open science. The momentum that FAIR has gained also allows us to bring other subjects to the attention of policy makers, including research software engineering, and increase the visibility of software sustainability concerns.</p>
<p>However, FAIR does not imply openness, FAIR does not ensure credit is given where credit is due, and FAIR does not give any guarantees with regard to quality. Stephan suggests that we should perhaps consider “FAIR PLAY” as the application of FAIR principles to software where useful, augmented with rigorously good practice for research software: open sourcing it per default, licensing it respectively, attributing contributions to it for credit, and asserting adequate quality. FAIR PLAY<sup>1</sup> is essentially the good things of FAIR combined with the good things of RSEing.</p>
<p>An important part of giving proper attribution is to make your software citable and to cite others when you build upon their work. Stephan and others have developed the <a href="https://citation-file-format.github.io/" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Citation File Format</a>, a metadata format for both humans and machines. While these citation files can be read and manually written, there is also an entire toolbox available to support creation, validation, and conversion of CFF files, and automation is on the horizon, with build plugins and automated updates.</p>
<p>Stephan’s slides are available <a href="https://sdruskat.net/2019-11-21-nl-escience-symposium/" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">here</a>.</p>
<h2 id="pablo-rodríguez-sánchez-how-software-development-shaped-the-way-i-write-science"><a href="#pablo-rodr%C3%ADguez-s%C3%A1nchez-how-software-development-shaped-the-way-i-write-science" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"><span class="icon icon-link"></span></a>Pablo Rodríguez-Sánchez: How software development shaped the way I write science</h2>
<p><img alt="Pablo Rodríguez-Sánchez: How software development shaped the way I write science" src="/img/fair-software-escience/pablo.jpg"></p>
<p>Pablo Rodríguez-Sánchez is working as an RSE at the Netherlands eScience Center. His talk was about how software development shaped the way he writes about his research.</p>
<p>With a great example of communication between Johannes Kepler and Galileo Galilei, Pablo confronted the audience with the fact that, despite great advances in the means of information and communication technology, some parts of scientific communication have not improved over the last four hundred years.</p>
<p>Pablo defines a scientific paper as a trustworthy and useful piece of encapsulated knowledge, and argues that there are actually many parallels between scientific papers and software. Both should adhere to the properties: consistency, reproducibility, being properly written, having references/dependencies, written by a team, and evolving over time. Instead of only using software development tools to write his paper, Pablo, inspired in what other researchers did before, takes it one step further and writes software packages whose output is the paper.</p>
<p>Using a combination of markdown and knitr, Pablo writes his papers as software packages in a way that all of the content of the paper, graphs and all can be fully reproduced by others who run the software.</p>
<p>Pablo’s slides are available <a href="https://pabrod.github.io/NLeSC_symp19-en.html#NLeSC_symp19" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">here</a>.</p>
<h2 id="panel-discussion"><a href="#panel-discussion" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"><span class="icon icon-link"></span></a>Panel Discussion</h2>
<p>Following the tree talks our speakers gathered on one side of the table for the panel discussion. While Ben was chairing the discussion, James was analyzing the questions that were submitted to mentimeter. The discussion involved questions such as:</p>
<ul>
<li>What does metadata mean in the context of software?</li>
<li>How to make software dependencies FAIR as well?</li>
<li>Should FAIR Software imply open source?</li>
<li>Does FAIR/Open Software conflict with the university’s striving for spin-offs/patents/commercialization?</li>
<li>The discussions are all quite abstract, what can we do concretely?</li>
</ul>
<p>Anna-Lena, Stephan, Pablo and also several attendees of the session shared their insights, experiences, perspectives and some speculations, making it a lively and inspiring session.</p>
<p>With regard to the question what to do concretely, Pablo mentioned “that the main bottleneck for FAIR software is, still, much more basic: many researchers who would like to share their code with FAIRness just don’t know how to begin.” In an effort to provide some concrete pointers on where to begin with making software FAIR, the Netherlands eScience Center and DANS developed fair-software.nl, which was officially launched later that day at the symposium.</p>
<p>If you would like to join the discussion on FAIR Software, the session’s organizers and the speakers of this session will be using the #fair-software on the RSE slack server to continue the discussion on FAIR Software.</p>
<hr>
<p><sup>1</sup> In case anyone has been wondering, “FAIR PLAY” of course stands for Findable, Accessible, Interoperable, Reusable, and Per default open source, Licensed, Attributing contributions to software for credit, and of adequate qualitY.</p>
            ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Request for comments -- Raising the Profile of Research Software]]></title>
            <link>/posts/2019-09-17-RaisingResearchSoftware</link>
            <guid>Request for comments -- Raising the Profile of Research Software</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 17 Sep 2019 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[
              <p>
                <img
                  alt="Cover image"
                  src="/img/Black_hole_-_Messier_87_crop_max_res.jpg"
                >
              </p>
              <p><em>Image credit: EHT Collaboration</em></p>
<h2 id="tldr"><a href="#tldr" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"><span class="icon icon-link"></span></a>TL;DR</h2>
<p><a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.3378571" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Read our paper</a> and <a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/16ABv4u6HADzkQHSiCQC1cPLVmA3EWWvr0B-DeZt1DGE/edit?usp=sharing" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">share your comments</a>.</p>
<p>This blog post was also is also poster <a href="https://openworking.wordpress.com/2019/09/17/request-for-comments-raising-the-profile-of-research-software/" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">here</a>.</p>
<p>In March 2019, a group of active members of the research software community in the Netherlands had a meeting with NWO (The Netherlands Organisation for Scientific Research)  to discuss the importance of research software in contemporary research and its relationship to research data, open science, and reproducibility in research (please see <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.2647436" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Making Research Software a First-Class Citizen in Research</a>).</p>
<!--break-->
<p>Following from that discussion, the group produced the position paper <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.3378571" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">“Raising the Profile of Research Software”</a>. The aim of the paper is to provide funding agencies and research institutions with concrete recommendations for raising the profile of research software.</p>
<p>And now we would like to bring more attention to this <strong>community</strong> effort. We are very interested in hearing your feedback. <a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/16ABv4u6HADzkQHSiCQC1cPLVmA3EWWvr0B-DeZt1DGE/edit?usp=sharing" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Please share your comments and suggestions</a> -- we will collect more opinions during the <a href="https://rse.ac.uk/conf2019/" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">UK-RSE</a> and <a href="https://nl-rse.org/events/NL-RSE19.html" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">NL-RSE</a> conferences to strengthen and improve these recommendations.</p>
<h2 id="what-is-the-paper-about"><a href="#what-is-the-paper-about" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"><span class="icon icon-link"></span></a>What is the paper about?</h2>
<p>Software has become a crucial part of research, but it still does not receive the same recognition as other research outputs. There is a need to fully acknowledge that research software is as important as research data and scientific publications, as expressed in DORA. We share the Research Software Alliance’s vision that research software should be “recognised and valued as a fundamental and vital component of research.”</p>
<p>We have provided recommendations which funding agencies and research institutions can implement to achieve this goal. These recommendations do not offer a full solution to addressing this issue, but provide a further step in the direction of achieving recognition for research software as a fundamental and vital component of research.</p>
<p>We believe that even minor policy improvements in the domain of research software will lead to visible improvement in science and suggest to funding and research institutions to adopt at least a part of our suggestions.</p>
<h3 id="authors-alphabetically"><a href="#authors-alphabetically" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"><span class="icon icon-link"></span></a>Authors (alphabetically):</h3>
<p>Anton Akhmerov, Maria Cruz, Niels Drost, Cees Hof, Tomas Knapen, Mateusz Kuzak, Carlos Martinez-Ortiz, Yasemin Turkyilmaz-van der Velden, Ben van Werkhoven</p>
            ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Call for contributions - NL-RSE19]]></title>
            <link>/posts/2019-07-09-NL-RSE-2019</link>
            <guid>Call for contributions - NL-RSE19</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 09 Jul 2019 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[
              <p>
                <img
                  alt="Cover image"
                  src="/img/conference-banner-flatv2.jpg"
                >
              </p>
              <p>Following the meetup in 2018, and the growing number of RSE events in the UK and Germany, NL-RSE is organizing the first full day event this year: <a href="https://nl-rse.org/events/NL-RSE19.html" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">NL-RSE19</a>! The conference will take place on the 20th of November, at the Johan Cruijff ArenA, Amsterdam.</p>
<!--break-->
<p><a href="events/NL-RSE19.html">NL-RSE19</a> is co-located with the <a href="https://www.esciencesymposium2019.nl/" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">National eScience Symposium 2019</a> taking place the following day, and we greatly appreciate the <a href="https://www.esciencecenter.nl/" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Netherlands eScience Center</a> for sponsoring the venue.</p>
<p>We hope to provide an inspiring program, and welcome talks, posters, and workshops on both technical and other topics related to Research Software Engineers. We very much welcome first time presenters.</p>
<h2 id="timeline"><a href="#timeline" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"><span class="icon icon-link"></span></a>Timeline</h2>
<ul>
<li><strong>27 September 2019 - Extended Deadline for submissions</strong></li>
<li>18 October 2019 - Notification of acceptance and program</li>
<li>20 November 2019 - NL-RSE19 conference</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="who-should-submit"><a href="#who-should-submit" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"><span class="icon icon-link"></span></a>Who should submit?</h2>
<p>We welcome submissions from anyone involved or related to research software, including:</p>
<ul>
<li>Researchers who develop software for research purposes</li>
<li>Software developers working in a research context</li>
<li>People from any organisation providing services to facilitate research software: tools makers, infrastructure providers, computing services, data centers, etc.</li>
<li>Anyone with a stake in research software (funders, publishers, decision makers, etc).</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="practicalities"><a href="#practicalities" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"><span class="icon icon-link"></span></a>Practicalities</h2>
<p>Please note that all contributions should be in English.
The registration fee for NL-RSE19 will be EUR 25, with requests for a waiver of this fee possible.</p>
<h2 id="talks"><a href="#talks" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"><span class="icon icon-link"></span></a>Talks</h2>
<p>Talks may have a length of 20 mins, including 5 mins for Q&#x26;A and discussion, depending on the number of talks in the respective session. If your talk is accepted, you will be notified about the length of the talk by the session chair.</p>
<h2 id="workshops"><a href="#workshops" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"><span class="icon icon-link"></span></a>Workshops</h2>
<p>Workshops are interactive sessions that give attendees the chance to collaborate on a specific topic. They may take different forms, e.g., as hands-on tutorial, discussion and speed-blogging session, hack session, etc. Workshops run over a length of up to 90 minutes.</p>
<h2 id="posters"><a href="#posters" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"><span class="icon icon-link"></span></a>Posters</h2>
<p>Posters will be displayed during the Posters &#x26; Drinks session. Each poster will also have the chance to pitch their poster during the plenary session, to attract people to visit your poster.</p>
<h2 id="submission"><a href="#submission" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"><span class="icon icon-link"></span></a>Submission</h2>
<p>To submit your contribution, fill in the <a href="https://forms.gle/FwR7hhpGkEBcqtQ98" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">submission form</a>.</p>
<h2 id="contact"><a href="#contact" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"><span class="icon icon-link"></span></a>Contact</h2>
<p>For updates about NL-RSE19, please visit <a href="https://nl-rse.org/events/NL-RSE19.html" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">the event page</a>.</p>
<p>If you have any questions, please contact us at <a href="mailto:conference@nl-rse.org">conference@nl-rse.org</a></p>
            ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[RSE Survey 2018 Results are in!]]></title>
            <link>/posts/2019-07-01-RSE-Survey-2018-results</link>
            <guid>RSE Survey 2018 Results are in!</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jul 2019 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[
              <p>
                <img
                  alt="Cover image"
                  src="/img/survey2018/map.png"
                >
              </p>
              <p>By Ben van Werkhoven, NL-RSE</p>
<p>The results from the <a href="https://www.software.ac.uk/blog/2019-02-15-rse-survey-2018-results" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">yearly International RSE Survey have been published
already</a>, but we haven't actually shared the
results for RSEs in the Netherlands yet! In this article, we'll give you a brief summary of the results specific to the
Netherlands!</p>
<!--break-->
<h2 id="employment"><a href="#employment" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"><span class="icon icon-link"></span></a>Employment</h2>
<p>We'll start of by taking a look at where RSEs are working in the Netherlands. We can see from the data that RSEs are still spread
across a large number of Universities and Institutes, but the majority works at a Dutch University.</p>
<p><img alt="At what type of organisation do you work?" src="/img/survey2018/organisation.png"></p>
<p>In the 2017 RSE Survey, we noticed that about 64% of RSEs have a permanent position and roughly 34% has a fixed-term position, with the last 2% having
a different nature of employment. In the 2018 survey, more detailed answering options were available and as such we can look at the nature of employment
of RSEs in the Netherlands in more detail.</p>
<p><img alt="What is the nature of your employment?" src="/img/survey2018/type_contract.png"></p>
<p>We can still see that over 58% of respondents have some form of permanent position, where as about 36% has some form of fixed-term position, and 3.6% of RSEs are self employed. The results are slightly different from 2017, but we cannot say yet if this is a trend over time or due to fact
that each survey is a different sample from the population of RSEs in the Netherlands.</p>
<p>When working in an academic environment it is essential for your carreer that you can show the impact of your work and your contributions to
science through publications. In 2017, the survey contained the question "Were you acknowledged in the paper?" to which respondents
could answer yes or no. Then, about 75% of RSEs answered that they were acknowledged in scientific publications about research
to which their software was crucial. Because acknowledgement can come in many different forms, the 2018 survey included for more specific answers.
So now we can have a look at exactly how RSEs are acknowledged for their work in scientific publications.</p>
<p><img alt="Acknowledgement of RSE work in scientific publications" src="/img/survey2018/paper_ack.png"></p>
<p>As we can see, the number of RSEs that are acknowledged as main or co-author does not add up to 75%, as some RSEs are only
acknowledged in the maintext or acknowledgements. Still, about 19.2% of RSEs answered that their work was not at all acknowledged,
which is very bad and can be damaging for their carreer.</p>
<h2 id="technical"><a href="#technical" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"><span class="icon icon-link"></span></a>Technical</h2>
<p>The 2018 survey contained several questions about the technical aspects of the work of RSEs. The survey asked RSEs about their
practice with regard to open source, software citation, and their use of DOIs through the following questions:</p>
<ul>
<li>How often do you use an open-source licence for your software?</li>
<li>How often do you reference software directly or the papers describing the software?'</li>
<li>How often do you associate your software with a Digital Object Identifier (DOI)?</li>
</ul>
<p><img alt="Software best practices by RSEs" src="/img/survey2018/best_practices.png"></p>
<p>Because the answers could be given on a scale from 1 (None at all) to 10 (All the time) we also show the results on this scale. It
seems that using open source licences for software is very common practice among RSEs. The same appears to be true for citing
software or software papers in scientific publications. It seems however that it's far less common for RSEs to associate their
software with a DOI. It might be worth noting that tools like Zenodo can automatically generate a DOI for you everytime you make a
new release of your software on GitHub.</p>
<p><img alt="The popular programming languages among RSEs" src="/img/survey2018/prog_lang.png"></p>
<p>Of course, the choice of programming language is something that all software developers can have lunch-debates about forever. And
as with all things the 'best' language is depends on what you are trying do. However, among RSEs we do have a clear winner, as it
seems that Python is the prevalent programming language according to RSEs participating in the survey. Note that respondents
could select multiple languages as part of their answer.</p>
<p><img alt="The OS RSEs are using" src="/img/survey2018/OS.png"></p>
<p>As expected, any flavor of Linux is still the dominant choice of operating system for RSEs when developing research software.</p>
<p><img alt="The types of version control systems RSEs are using" src="/img/survey2018/version_control.png"></p>
<p>Version control is indispensable when developing software and the this also holds for research software. As such, the survey inquired
what kind of version control system RSEs are using for their software development. It turns out, unsurprisingly perhaps, that Git is
by far the most popular.</p>
<h2 id="national-rse-organization"><a href="#national-rse-organization" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"><span class="icon icon-link"></span></a>National RSE organization</h2>
<p>A set of questions from the survey was of particular interest to NL-RSE, since it was about what NL-RSE could do for the
RSEs in the Netherlands. The first question we'll look into is: "What would you hope to get out of a national RSE
association?"</p>
<p><img alt="What do you think is important for NL-RSE?" src="/img/survey2018/nl-rse-goals.png"></p>
<p>We can see that what RSEs hope to get from NL-RSE is actually diverse. Although the largest theme you could say is on
networking, finding job opportunities, and research collaborations. However, training and software development practices
also deserve our attention. If you like to organize events, give trainings, or work on software development standards,
please consider becoming actively involved with NL-RSE! We are always looking for new active members! Please send an email
to <a href="mailto:info@nl-rse.org">info@nl-rse.org</a>.</p>
<p><img alt="Would RSEs attend a national RSE event?" src="/img/survey2018/join-RSE-event.png"></p>
<p>The final question that we'll discuss here is another very interesting one! Would you like to attend a national RSE event?
An overwhelming number of RSEs in the Netherlands answered YES to this question! And for those of you, we have good news!
NL-RSE will be organizing a first NL-RSE conference in November 2019! Be sure to <a href="/pages/join.html">join the NL-RSE mailinglist</a>
to stay up to date on information about the event.</p>
            ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[deRSE 2019: First conference for Research Software Engineers in Germany]]></title>
            <link>/posts/2019-06-24-deRSE</link>
            <guid>deRSE 2019: First conference for Research Software Engineers in Germany</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 24 Jun 2019 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[
              <p>
                <img
                  alt="Cover image"
                  src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/4096/1*v-AmdN95tAiNrpO9EMc86g.jpeg"
                >
              </p>
              <p>Written by Carlos Martinez-Ortiz and Florian Huber</p>
<h2 id="facts"><a href="#facts" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"><span class="icon icon-link"></span></a>Facts</h2>
<p><strong>What:</strong> <a href="https://www.de-rse.org/en/conf2019/" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">First Conference for Research Software Engineers</a> (RSE) in Germany<br>
<strong>When:</strong> 4-6 June 2019<br>
<strong>Where:</strong> Albert Einstein Science Park in Potsdam</p>
<!--break-->
<h2 id="but-wait-what-is-a-rse-anyway"><a href="#but-wait-what-is-a-rse-anyway" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"><span class="icon icon-link"></span></a>But wait… what is a RSE anyway?</h2>
<p>Like many other areas of society, the field of scientific research currently sees a quickly growing influence of new digital technologies and new IT concepts. Not surprisingly, this results in an ever-increasing need for people to tackle the increasing digitalization of research.</p>
<p>In the past, people in many different positions within the academic landscape would take care of developing digital tools such as research software. Typically this included many PhD students and postdocs, hence positions with deviating job profiles and non-permanent contracts.</p>
<p>In view of the rising need for digital expertise and the missing adequate positions and job descriptions within most academic systems, an initiative to establish a dedicated profession of the Research Software Engineer (<strong>RSE</strong>) was started.</p>
<p><img alt="deRSE19 aerial group photo (CC-BY Antonia Cozacu, Jan Philipp Dietrich, de-RSE e.V.)" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/4096/1*v-AmdN95tAiNrpO9EMc86g.jpeg"><em>deRSE19 aerial group photo (CC-BY Antonia Cozacu, Jan Philipp Dietrich, de-RSE e.V.)</em></p>
<p>This initiative started in the UK with the <a href="https://rse.ac.uk/" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">UK Research Software Engineer Association</a> (see also <a href="https://www.software.ac.uk/blog/2016-08-17-not-so-brief-history-research-software-engineers-0" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">the not-so-brief history of RSEs</a>). Several countries followed and founded RSE organizations including the Netherlands (<a href="http://nl-rse.org/" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">NL-RSE</a>) and Germany (<a href="http://nl-rse.org/" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">deRSE</a>).</p>
<p>As <a href="https://twitter.com/alysbrett" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Alys Brett</a> pointed out during her keynote, RSEs sit somewhere in between a researcher and a software engineer. The term RSE is still somewhat vague as it covers a broad spectrum of expertise and activities; there are no universal job specification or career paths defined for RSEs, <a href="https://www.kdl.kcl.ac.uk/blog/rse-career-development/" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">although some initiatives are emerging</a>. Many people may be a RSE without realizing it!</p>
<p><img alt="Slide from the presenation of Alys Brett pointing at the position of RSEs in between Software Engineering and Research." src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/2000/0*LHILpQZNZqtPdkhb"><br>
<em>Slide from the presenation of Alys Brett pointing at the position of RSEs in between Software Engineering and Research.</em></p>
<p>If we think of RSEs as individuals which combine (in different proportions) software engineering skills &#x26; scientific research skills then it indeed covers a very broad range. This means the RSE community is in itself very diverse, which has the advantage of diversity of knowledge and expertise. However, the downside of this diversity is that it is difficult to put a RSE in a box and clearly identify who is a RSE.</p>
<p><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/2000/0*J3KDe8ySfpOxzb3Z"></p>
<h2 id="rse-demographics"><a href="#rse-demographics" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"><span class="icon icon-link"></span></a>RSE demographics</h2>
<p>So, is this just a small group of people? Not really — since 2016, an <a href="https://github.com/softwaresaved/international-survey/tree/master/analysis/2018" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">international survey</a> is conducted, asking individuals questions regarding their education, field of expertise, technical skills and demographic information. During the conference, <a href="https://twitter.com/StephanJanosch" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Stephan Janosch</a> and <a href="https://twitter.com/mrtnhmtz" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Martin Hammitzsch</a> used this survey to give an impression of how the RSE landscape looks like in Germany. A similar analysis was conducted at <a href="https://www.dlr.de/dlr/en/" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">DLR</a>, although some people at DLR do not identify as RSEs but as researchers which do software (<a href="https://derse19.uni-jena.de/derse19/talk/MQCZ3N/" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">see talk abstract</a>).</p>
<p><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/2000/0*m9ogy5N0x0CX1h7C"></p>
<p>In general, the RSE landscape looks very similar to the current situation in the Netherlands. It still is a long way to go to establish the role of RSEs within the academic landscape. One indicator is the large fraction of non-permanent contracts among RSEs (see bar plots below). Another one is that actual job titles in Germany still show the lack of dedicated positions related to research software engineering (see word clouds below).</p>
<p>It at first seems as if RSEs in the Netherlands can already rely a better job situation (more permanent positions) and better fitting job titles. However, bare in mind that the number of respondents in Germany was higher than in the Netherlands: 333 vs 54 which may induce some bias in the statistics. The numbers also heavily depend on who considers herself/himself a RSE. Hence who is actually responding to the survey. In the Netherlands we believe that a large number of participants working at the eScience Center dominate the statistics.</p>
<p><img alt="Plots from (or based on) a 2018 RSE survey. A larger fraction of RSEs in the Netherlands holds a permanent position (bar plots on the left. Permanent RSE employment: 57% vs 25% in Germany). And RSE-related job titles are still not common in the German academic setting (Job title wordclouds on the right. Top right: Netherlands. Bottom right: Germany). Both aspects will hopefully change through the actions of the RSE initiative. Also be aware that statistics for the Netherlands were fairly low for the survey and are likely to be dominated by people from the Netherlands eScience Center." src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/7600/1*0n9pVvWQSfDUDrwJdSDrEw.png"><em>Plots from (or based on) a <a href="https://github.com/softwaresaved/international-survey/tree/master/analysis/2018" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">2018 RSE survey</a>. A larger fraction of RSEs in the Netherlands holds a permanent position (bar plots on the left. Permanent RSE employment: 57% vs 25% in Germany). And RSE-related job titles are still not common in the German academic setting (Job title wordclouds on the right. Top right: Netherlands. Bottom right: Germany). Both aspects will hopefully change through the actions of the RSE initiative. Also be aware that statistics for the Netherlands were fairly low for the survey and are likely to be dominated by people from the Netherlands eScience Center.</em></p>
<h2 id="what-will-the-future-bring-for-rses"><a href="#what-will-the-future-bring-for-rses" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"><span class="icon icon-link"></span></a>What will the future bring for RSE’s</h2>
<p>We don’t know — undoubtedly research software will continue to play an important part in science and with it the role of RSEs will become more prominent.</p>
<p>What we do know for sure is that deRSE was a fantastic conference and a great success! And it reminded us that would be very beneficial for the RSE community in the Netherlands to have another local RSE conference (we had a <a href="http://nl-rse.org/2018/06/29/first-meetup.html" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">first meet-up last year</a>) where RSEs from different institutions can come together and share their experiences and thoughts. <a href="http://nl-rse.org/pages/join.html" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Join the NL-RSE mailing list</a> for updates on upcoming RSE events in the Netherlands.</p>
<h2 id="some-impressions-from-the-conference"><a href="#some-impressions-from-the-conference" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"><span class="icon icon-link"></span></a>Some impressions from the conference</h2>
<p>Over the three days of the conference we saw a lot of interesting presentations, posters, attended workshops and discussion sessions. Clearly too much to do all contributions justice. Here we just picked a few highlights that stuck with us and were not mentioned above:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>The secret behind the growth of RSE Groups in the UK (see <a href="https://www.software.ac.uk/blog/2018-04-11-secret-behind-growth-rse-groups-uk" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">their blog post</a>).</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><a href="https://twitter.com/AndreasZeller" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Andreas Zeller</a> gave a great entertaining keynote lecture on Sustainable Research Software. His suggestion was to use literate programming as well as prototyping.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>*Literate programming+ Prototyping = <strong>Literate prototyping</strong> = Notebooks
*(see also the <a href="https://blog.esciencecenter.nl/entangled-1744448f4b9f" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">recent post on literate programming</a> by <a href="undefined">Johan Hidding</a>)</p>
<ul>
<li>There were about 40 posters and most of them were very briefly (1 minute) pitched in a special lightening session. This made it very clear how broad the audience was in terms of backgrounds and scientific research fields.</li>
</ul>
<p><img alt="Presenters of brief poster pitches during the lightening session." src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/3200/0*wfJTIrrkE3tX3ppF"><em>Presenters of brief poster pitches during the lightening session.</em></p>
<ul>
<li>
<p><a href="https://twitter.com/konradfoerstner" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Konrad Förstner</a> did <a href="http://www.openscienceradio.org/2019/06/12/osr171-voices-from-de-rse-conference-2019-en/" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">a Podcast</a> during the conference and collected impressions from many of the participants (which again shows how diverse the field is!).</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><a href="https://twitter.com/alexhillphd" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Alex Hill</a> was making a strong case for doing more reviews in her talk</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>(she also wrote a <a href="http://www.alexandra-hill.com/2018/06/25/the-art-of-giving-and-receiving-code-reviews/" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">blog post on the same topic</a>).</p>
<h2 id="final-notes"><a href="#final-notes" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"><span class="icon icon-link"></span></a>Final notes</h2>
<p>Many of the presentations were recorded and will soon be made available. Best to check out updates on their <a href="https://twitter.com/RSE_de" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">twitter channel</a> or the <a href="https://www.de-rse.org/en/conf2019/index.html" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">conference website</a>.
Attending this conference was a lot of fun, so thanks for organizing and see you next time!</p>
<p>Any comments, suggestions, or questions?<br>
Get in touch!<br>
<a href="https://twitter.com/neocarlitos" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Carlos on twitter</a><br>
<a href="https://twitter.com/me_datapoint" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Florian on twitter</a></p>
            ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[First Meetup of the Netherlands Research Software Engineer Community]]></title>
            <link>/posts/2018-09-20-First-NL-RSE-Meetup</link>
            <guid>First Meetup of the Netherlands Research Software Engineer Community</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 20 Sep 2018 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[
              <p>
                <img
                  alt="Cover image"
                  src="/img/group_picture.jpg"
                >
              </p>
              <p>We had a great first meetup of the NL-RSE community with around 40 participants!
A big thanks everyone attending for making this such a great meeting!</p>
<!--break-->
<p>The meetup was kicked-off by Niels Drost and Mateusz Kuzak with an introduction of the program for the day.
This was followed by <a href="http://nl-rse.org/resources/20180920/keynote-ilian-todorov.pdf" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Ilian Todorov</a>, who
gave a keynote presentation about the RSE movement in the UK, how it was founded, and their plans for the future.
Next, Ben van Werkhoven gave an overview of the current state of the NL-RSE community with an introduction of the
NL-RSE Core team, and an overview of the RSE Survey results from 2017.</p>
<p>After the coffee break we broke off into different discussion groups on various topics, including:</p>
<ul>
<li>RSE as an official job title</li>
<li>Education</li>
<li>Talking to IT departments</li>
<li>Enabling independent RSEs</li>
<li>Software development best practices and RSE training</li>
<li>Place in Science and within organisations</li>
</ul>
<p>Each group presented the outcome of their discussions and how they plan to follow up on the topic. After this we reserved
some time for taking a group picture, networking, and drinks. It was really great to see so many unfamiliar faces and meet
fellow RSEs from all over the Netherlands!</p>
<p>We plan to organize another event in November 2019 and look forward to seeing everyone again at that time!</p>
            ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[First Meetup of the Netherlands Research Software Engineer Community - register Now!]]></title>
            <link>/posts/2018-06-29-first-meetup</link>
            <guid>First Meetup of the Netherlands Research Software Engineer Community - register Now!</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 29 Jun 2018 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[
              <p>
                <img
                  alt="Cover image"
                  src="https://www.expatica.com/app/uploads/sites/3/2014/05/utrecht.jpg"
                >
              </p>
              <p><strong>When: 20 September 2018</strong></p>
<p><strong>Where: <a href="http://jim.spaces.nexudus.com/en" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Jaarbeurs Innovation Mile (JIM)</a> in Utrecht</strong></p>
<p><strong>Time: 13:00 - 17:30</strong></p>
<!--break-->
<p><strong>Registration: via <a href="https://docs.google.com/forms/d/e/1FAIpQLSfCfzK1D6hsqVLkKgPGQ74i55pzV5DIvONCpRwCC1hXfda-ag/viewform" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Google Form</a></strong></p>
<p>Registration is open for the first meeting of the Netherlands Research Software Engineers Community (<a href="http://nl-rse.org/" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">NL-RSE.org</a>). This event will provide a unique opportunity to those who develop and contribute to research software in the Netherlands to come together and help shape up this recently started community, which follows on the success of similar initiatives in the <a href="https://rse.ac.uk/" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">UK</a> and <a href="http://www.de-rse.org/de/" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Germany</a>.</p>
<h3 id="who-should-attend"><a href="#who-should-attend" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"><span class="icon icon-link"></span></a>Who should attend?</h3>
<ul>
<li>Whether you work at a Dutch academic institution, national research facility or knowledge institute, commercial company or any other organisation...</li>
<li>Whether you see yourself as professional software developer, a researcher who spends  time coding, or a mix of both...</li>
</ul>
<p>...if you write or contribute to research software in the Netherlands and beyond, then you should attend.</p>
<h3 id="what-to-expect"><a href="#what-to-expect" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"><span class="icon icon-link"></span></a>What to expect</h3>
<p>The program will include short keynote speeches, interactive sessions, and plenty of time for discussion and networking. One of the goals of the event is to bring together everyone in the Netherlands who has an interest in research software and identify the topics that are important and of common interest to the community. In true Dutch style, there will also be time for beer and bitterballen at the end!</p>
<p>The meeting will be in English and the capacity will be limited to around 60 participants. Therefore, please register soon as you can, as the registration form will close when full capacity is reached.</p>
<h3 id="detailed-program"><a href="#detailed-program" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"><span class="icon icon-link"></span></a>Detailed program</h3>
<p>12:30 Arrival with Coffee<br>
13:00 <a href="http://nl-rse.org/resources/20180920/nl-rse-meeting-intro.pdf" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Welcome, Purpose of the meeting</a><br>
13:15 <a href="http://nl-rse.org/resources/20180920/keynote-ilian-todorov.pdf" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Keynote by Ilian Todorov: The UK-RSE movement</a><br>
14:00 <a href="http://nl-rse.org/resources/20180920/nl-rse-introduction.pdf" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Introducing: NL-RSE by Ben van Werkhoven</a><br>
14:15 Coffee break<br>
14:45 Breakout in groups to discuss topics<br>
16:00 Wrap-up, short presentations of results by breakout groups<br>
16:30 Borrel<br>
17:30 end</p>
<h3 id="directions"><a href="#directions" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"><span class="icon icon-link"></span></a>Directions</h3>
<p>Jaarbeurs Innovation Mile (JIM), 6th floor Beatrixgebouw<br>
Jaarbeursplein 6, 3521 AL Utrecht<br>
after entering JIM ask hostess for "Tribune"</p>
<p>Google maps location:</p>
<div class="mapouter"><div class="gmap_canvas"><iframe width="600" height="500" id="gmap_canvas" src="https://maps.google.com/maps?q=jaarbeurs%20innovation%20mile%20utrecht&#x26;t=&#x26;z=17&#x26;ie=UTF8&#x26;iwloc=&#x26;output=embed" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" marginheight="0" marginwidth="0"></iframe></div><style>.mapouter{text-align:right;height:500px;width:600px;}.gmap_canvas {overflow:hidden;background:none!important;height:500px;width:600px;}</style></div>
            ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Introducing NL-RSE]]></title>
            <link>/posts/2017-12-20-introducing-nl-rse</link>
            <guid>Introducing NL-RSE</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 20 Dec 2017 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[
              <p>
                <img
                  alt="Cover image"
                  src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/10944/1*LmBD9OaRAJPnBYBoZwyZMw.jpeg"
                >
              </p>
              <p><em>Bootstrapping the community of Research Software Engineers in the Netherlands</em></p>
<p>Research software has become an indispensable instrument for virtually every academic researcher. A case in point: <a href="http://dx.doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.14809" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">survey data</a> from the UK revealed that 92% of academics use research software, 69% say that their research would not be practical without it and 56% develop their own software. Creating, storing and analyzing data is crucial in researchers’ daily work and enables them to address increasingly challenging research questions.</p>
<p>This rapid digitization of research has strongly increased the number of people writing and contributing to research software. This is part of a more general trend, where positions like <a href="https://www.tudelft.nl/en/library/theme-portals/research-data-management/research-data-management/data-stewardship/" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">*data stewards</a>*, <em>information managers</em>, research data officer, <em>research supporter</em> and other non-traditional research positions are becoming increasingly recognized as intrinsic positions in the academic research ecosystem. To increase the impact, recognition and visibility of research software in academia, we (<a href="https://escience-platform.nl/" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">ePlan</a> and the Netherlands eScience Center) have taken the initiative to start and support the community of professionals *behind *the software: the Netherlands Research Software Engineers community: <a href="http://nl-rse.org/" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">NL-RSE</a>.</p>
<p>The goal of the NL-RSE community fits with the broader national and international open science movement. For example in the Dutch <a href="https://www.openscience.nl/en/" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">National Platform Open Science</a> and the <a href="http://ec.europa.eu/research/openscience/index.cfm?pg=open-science-cloud" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">European Open Science Cloud</a> and <a href="https://www.go-fair.org/" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">GO-FAIR</a>, there is a strong focus on new and digital technologies — <em>including software</em> — to make research data, methods and outcomes more accessible and better reusable.</p>
<p><img alt="http://nl-rse.org/" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/6286/1*Do0XW7EAl1W5p5L9iuE6lQ.png"><em><a href="http://nl-rse.org/" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">http://nl-rse.org/</a></em></p>
<p>NL-RSE is an open community for all people who as (part of) their job are writing software, regardless of the academic discipline or research area. Being member of the community allows research software engineers in the Netherlands to share knowledge, to initiate collaborations and to offer and ask support from other engineers in the Netherlands.</p>
<h2 id="tldr-version-of-this-blogpost"><a href="#tldr-version-of-this-blogpost" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"><span class="icon icon-link"></span></a>TL;DR version of this blogpost</h2>
<ul>
<li>
<p>Sign up to the NL-RSE community <a href="https://lists.nl-rse.org/mailman/listinfo/everyone" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">here</a></p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Fill in our survey here (edit — the survey was held in December 2017 and is now closed. We will soon publishing a link to the results)</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Visit the <a href="http://nl-rse.org/" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">website</a></p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Get in touch here: <a href="mailto:info@nl-rse.org">info@nl-rse.org</a></p>
</li>
</ul>
<p><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/2000/0*w8y_yDWcbi7OCF0o."></p>
<p>Source: <a href="https://dirkgorissen.com/2012/03/26/the-researcher-programmer-a-new-species/" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Dirk Gorissen</a></p>
<h2 id="the-dutch-guild-of-research-software-engineers"><a href="#the-dutch-guild-of-research-software-engineers" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"><span class="icon icon-link"></span></a>The Dutch guild of Research Software Engineers</h2>
<p><img alt="Research software has become an indispensable instrument for virtually every academic researcher" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/4096/1*cSXU4CeixL3HnY9LBOTXeQ.jpeg"><em>Research software has become an indispensable instrument for virtually every academic researcher</em></p>
<p>The increasing reliance on and use of data and digital techniques in academia has led to an ever increasing amount of research software at the very core of the science done. The emergence of research software has gone hand in hand with a strong growth in people who actually *develop *research software. Today, the UK at least counts more than <a href="http://rse.ac.uk/" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">800 </a>of professionals who identify as developers of software for research purposes. But for the Netherlands, we don’t know. Sure, we know that there are at least <a href="https://www.esciencecenter.nl/people" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">40 people</a> actively developing and applying research software in close collaboration with university researchers. But there are many more people throughout the country working on software, managing data, and supporting digital research, distributed over various research institutes, universities, and other knowledge organizations.</p>
<p>To strengthen the various communities and to increase interaction between them, we have taken the initiative to start the Research Software Engineer (RSE) community in the Netherlands. It is inspired by the successful <a href="http://rse.ac.uk/" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">UK-RSE Association</a>, as well as the inspirational visits to the <em>First conference of Research Software Engineers</em> in 2016, events organized by the Software Sustainability Institute, and encounters with UK-RSE and <a href="http://www.de-rse.org" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">DE-RSE</a> members.</p>
<h2 id="why-the-term-research-software-engineer-rse"><a href="#why-the-term-research-software-engineer-rse" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"><span class="icon icon-link"></span></a>Why the term Research Software Engineer (RSE)?</h2>
<p>Without a name, it is difficult to refer to a group of people that share a set of skills and characteristics. A name must be descriptive, yet short enough to be meaningful. It must differentiate and be acceptable to both the people who identify with it and the academic community. In 2012, when trying to form a community of people working on software in academia in the UK, a lot of thought and discussion went into what term to use. Eventually, the new name was created by fusing the two skills that make it unique: an understanding of both research *and *software engineering. Quoting from the paper that marked the start of the Research Software Engineer community in the UK:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>*Research institutions need individuals with a new professional designation — the research software engineer. These individuals combine a professional attitude to the exercise of software engineering with a deep understanding of research topics. They lead the design and construction of increasingly complex research software systems, and play an important part in the co-design of research requirements, understanding and addressing software engineering questions that arise in research planning. *[<a href="http://digital-research-2012.oerc.ox.ac.uk/papers/the-research-software-engineer/at_download/file" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Baxter et al., 2012</a>]</p>
</blockquote>
<p><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/4096/1*XWCrOtVijQ8gqcEWKuWMBA.jpeg"></p>
<p>RSEs are often embedded in research groups in small teams, or even by themselves, working hard on the software, algorithms, tools and interfaces that facilitate cutting-edge research. And in many cases, they are academic researchers at the same time, holding positions as (assistant/associate) professor, postdoc or PhD candidate. RSEs closely collaborate with researchers to understand the challenges they face, and then develop research software to provide the answers. Some have started as researchers who spent a lot of time developing software to do their research. Others have started as software developers who have developed a strong affinity with scientific research.</p>
<h2 id="building-the-community"><a href="#building-the-community" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"><span class="icon icon-link"></span></a>Building the Community</h2>
<p>Early 2017, ePlan and the eScience Center took the first steps to found NL-RSE. While we hope that the community will run independently at some point, for the time being a few enthusiastic organizations and partner organizations will take care of NL-RSE best we can. Upon learning of our plans, a number of organizations and individuals have already confirmed their interest in supporting NL-RSE. We are very happy to be joined by DTL in setting up NL-RSE, and hope others will follow. Be sure to send us an e-mail (<a href="mailto:info@nl-rse.org">info@nl-rse.org</a>) if you are interested in supporting NL-RSE!</p>
<p>Although supported by a number of organizations, the NL-RSE community consists of individuals self-identifying as Research Software Engineers. We feel this is the only way to truly build a community.</p>
<p>The centrepiece of the community is the mailing list. Rather than a newsletter governed by a communication department, any member can send messages to the entire community to make announcements. We also have created a <a href="https://nl-rse.slack.com/" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Slack Group</a> for discussions, and a <a href="http://nl-rse.org" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">website </a>with information.</p>
<p><img alt="“Better software better research” — slogan by the Software Sustainability Institute in the UK. https://software.ac.uk/about" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/2000/1*5xwpuYVUP73eMdxb7g5dyg.jpeg"><em>“Better software better research” — slogan by the Software Sustainability Institute in the UK. <a href="https://software.ac.uk/about" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">https://software.ac.uk/about</a></em></p>
<p>The main goal of NL-RSE is to build a community of Research Software Engineers in the Netherlands, build best practices, and learn from each other. Note that NL-RSE is about engineering of research software, rather than research on software engineering, a subtle but crucial difference with the computer science field of software engineering. We also hope to raise awareness of the importance of software in research, and the vital role RSEs play in creating this software. Besides an online presence, we plan to also hold irregular meetings inviting community members to meet up.</p>
<h2 id="fill-in-the-survey-edit-survey-closed-in-december-2017"><a href="#fill-in-the-survey-edit-survey-closed-in-december-2017" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"><span class="icon icon-link"></span></a>Fill in the Survey! (edit: survey closed in December 2017)</h2>
<p>We would like to get a better idea of the community, and to this end are conducting a survey, in cooperation with UK-RSE, where such a survey was held as well. The survey aims to generate insights into how many Research Software Engineers (RSEs) there are in the Netherlands, which academic disciplines they are active in, how they divide their work between research and software engineering, and what their career opportunities are within their organizations. There are 45 questions in the survey, which should take about 10 minutes to complete.</p>
<h2 id="join-nl-rse"><a href="#join-nl-rse" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"><span class="icon icon-link"></span></a>Join NL-RSE!</h2>
<p>If you identify as a Research Software Engineer, and are enthusiastic about joining a community of your peers, please <a href="https://lists.nl-rse.org/mailman/listinfo/everyone" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">sign up for our mailing list!</a> You can also follow us on Twitter, sign up for the Slack, or send us an <a href="mailto:info@nl-rse.org">email</a>.</p>
            ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[What is a Research Software Engineer?]]></title>
            <link>/posts/2017-06-13-what-is-rse</link>
            <guid>What is a Research Software Engineer?</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 13 Jun 2017 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[
              <p>
                <img
                  alt="Cover image"
                  src="https://www.xmple.com/wallpaper/pink-gradient-linear-1920x1080-c2-c0204f-511426-a-165-f-14.svg"
                >
              </p>
              <p>Research Software Engineers (RSEs) are the people that closely collaborate
with researchers to understand the challenges they face, and then develop
research software to provide the answers. Some have started as researchers
who spent a lot of time developing software to do their research. Others
have started as software developers who have developed a strong affinity
with scientific research.</p>
<p>While the RSEs are extremely valuable to the scientific community, they
currently lack a formal place in the academic system. This means
there is no easy way to recognise their contribution, to reward
them, or to represent their views.</p>
<p>Without a name, it is difficult for people to rally around a
cause, that is why the term Research Software Engineer was
created. We are now working, together with RSE associations in the
<a href="http://rse.ac.uk/" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">UK</a> and <a href="http://www.de-rse.org/de" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Germany</a>,
to raise awareness of the role, and to bring the
RSE community in the Netherlands together.</p>
            ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[NL-RSE election]]></title>
            <link>/events/NL-RSE-elections2021</link>
            <guid>NL-RSE election</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 16 Sep 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[
              <p>
                <img
                  alt="Cover image"
                  src="/img/element5-digital-T9CXBZLUvic-unsplash.jpg"
                >
              </p>
              <p>The current core team is made up of volunteers, who have taken the task of setting up the NL-RSE community.
As the NL-RSE community grows, the core team feels it is important to be transparent about how the core team is selected and what their responsibilities are. It is also important that the whole NL-RSE community has the opportunity to select who represents them in the core team. For this reason, this year we will be holding the first election in NL-RSE history!</p>
<!--break-->
<h2 id="who-is-eligible-to-vote"><a href="#who-is-eligible-to-vote" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"><span class="icon icon-link"></span></a>Who is eligible to vote?</h2>
<p>Anyone who is registered on the NL-RSE mailing list on 31th October 2021 is eligible to vote in the 2021 election.</p>
<h2 id="who-is-eligible-to-stand-for-election"><a href="#who-is-eligible-to-stand-for-election" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"><span class="icon icon-link"></span></a>Who is eligible to stand for election?</h2>
<p>Anyone who is registered on the NL-RSE mailing list on 15th October 2021 is eligible to be an election candidate in the 2021 election and must nominate him/herself by making this known to the <a href="https://nl-rse.org/pages/core-team.html#nl-rse-secretariat" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">NL-RSE secretariat</a>.</p>
<h2 id="important-dates"><a href="#important-dates" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"><span class="icon icon-link"></span></a>Important dates</h2>
<ul>
<li>31 October 2021 – deadline for becoming a candidate</li>
<li>1st November 2021 – official list of candidates will be published on the website</li>
<li>16 November 2021 – voting will take place via via electronic voting system</li>
<li>1st December 2021 – results will be announced during the December meetup and via the mailing list</li>
<li>1st January 2022 – the new core team office period will start</li>
</ul>
            ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[NL-RSE Road Show Event]]></title>
            <link>/events/NL-RSE-RSE21</link>
            <guid>NL-RSE Road Show Event</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 14 Sep 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[
              <p>
                <img
                  alt="Cover image"
                  src="/img/logos/Artwork - plural.png"
                >
              </p>
              <p>On 14th October 2021 the international RSE community will celebrate the 1st <a href="https://researchsoftware.org/2021/07/29/International-RSE-day.html" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">International RSE Day</a>. What is it? It is a celebration of RSEs and RSE work -- that means we want to celebrate <em>you</em> and <em>your work</em>!</p>
<!--break-->
<p>In connection to the international RSE day, we are organising our own local event: the NL-RSE Road Show Event (NL-RSE RSE). The aim is for it to be an inspirational event where RSEs from all over the country get to talk to each other, exchange their experiences and struggles, and are able to make new connections.</p>
<p>We would love for this to be an in-person event. However, given the uncertainty of the COVID situation, we do not think it is wise to encourage people to travel to a central location. For this reason, as a compromise, we would like to organise this event as a collection of connected local events (<a href="https://www.linkedin.com/pulse/using-hub-spoke-hybrid-live-events-re-engage-your-people-thewlis/" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Hub &#x26; spoke model</a>), with small local events connected to each other for a shared programme. Our aim is to minimise the need for travel to the event, while maximising the networking opportunity for participants. This will also give us the flexibility to switch to a fully online event if necessary.</p>
<h2 id="venues"><a href="#venues" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"><span class="icon icon-link"></span></a>Venues</h2>
<h3 id="utrecht"><a href="#utrecht" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"><span class="icon icon-link"></span></a>Utrecht</h3>
<ul>
<li>Details: You will need to bring your ticket &#x26; <a href="https://www.jaarbeurs.nl/nl/werkwijze-coronatoegangsbewijs" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">corona certificate</a>.</li>
<li>Address: The HUB - Tribune &#x26; Skybar, <a href="https://goo.gl/maps/mTaGAPot7ZUu7aj8A" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Jaarbeurs Innovation Mile (JIM), Jaarbeursplein 6, 3521 AL, Utrecht</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.eventbrite.co.uk/e/nl-rse-road-show-event-tickets-178646284847" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Get your ticket here</a></li>
</ul>
<h3 id="amsterdam-science-park"><a href="#amsterdam-science-park" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"><span class="icon icon-link"></span></a>Amsterdam Science Park</h3>
<ul>
<li>Details: You will need to bring your ticket.</li>
<li>Address: SURF building, VK1 &#x26; VK2 rooms, <a href="https://goo.gl/maps/NPzCTSvkCZHDH4bZA" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Science Park 140, 1098 XG Amsterdam</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.eventbrite.co.uk/e/nl-rse-road-show-event-tickets-178646284847" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Get your ticket here</a></li>
</ul>
<h3 id="online"><a href="#online" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"><span class="icon icon-link"></span></a>Online</h3>
<ul>
<li>Details: For participants who do not want or cannot join in person, we will host a virtual hub!</li>
<li>Address: Online</li>
<li><a href="https://www.eventbrite.co.uk/e/nl-rse-road-show-event-tickets-178646284847" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Get your ticket here</a></li>
</ul>
<h2 id="programme"><a href="#programme" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"><span class="icon icon-link"></span></a>Programme</h2>
<p>| -- | ---- |
| 14:00 | Welcome by location host (location joins zoom room) |
| 14:10 | Welcome by zoom host |
| 14:15 | <strong>Keynote</strong>: "The origins and future of Research Software Engineering" <br>by <a href="https://twitter.com/milliams" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Matt Williams</a> |
| 14:45 | World premiere RSE video |
| 15:00 |  NL-RSE election -- information session |
| 15:10 | Launch NL-RSE new website |
| 15:20 | Hello from different locations |
| 15:30 | Local Q&#x26;A session / sharing RSE experiences |
| 15:50 | Networking session (borrel) |</p>
            ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[September 15, 2021, NL-RSE Meetup]]></title>
            <link>/events/2021-09-15-meetup</link>
            <guid>September 15, 2021, NL-RSE Meetup</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 28 Jun 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[
              <p>
                <img
                  alt="Cover image"
                  src="/img/meetup-header-with-logo.jpg"
                >
              </p>
              <p>September 2021 Meetup of the NL-RSE Community.</p>
<!--break-->
<p><img alt="Logo Banner" src="/img/meetups/logo-banner.jpg"></p>
<h2 id="location"><a href="#location" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"><span class="icon icon-link"></span></a>Location</h2>
<p>The call will be conducted with the <a href="https://zoom.us" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">ZOOM</a> conferencing platform. Follow <a href="https://support.zoom.us/hc/en-us/articles/201362193-Joining-a-Meeting" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Joining the Meeting instructions</a>.</p>
<p>Zoom link will be sent to your email with your registration.</p>
<h2 id="registration"><a href="#registration" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"><span class="icon icon-link"></span></a>Registration</h2>
<p>The registration is free.</p>
<p>Please register via this <a href="https://www.eventbrite.co.uk/e/nl-rse-meetup-september-15-2021-tickets-161442710493" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Eventbrite page</a>.</p>
<h2 id="agenda"><a href="#agenda" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"><span class="icon icon-link"></span></a>Agenda</h2>



























































<table><thead><tr><th>Time</th><th>Responsible</th><th>Type</th><th>Subject</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>14:30 - 14:45</td><td></td><td></td><td>hello &#x26; coffee</td></tr><tr><td>14:45 - 15:00</td><td></td><td></td><td>Welcome and introductions</td></tr><tr><td>15:00 - 15:30</td><td>Adina Wagner</td><td>Talk</td><td>Data + Code + Software = PDF: How to write a reproducible research article</td></tr><tr><td>15:30 - 16:00</td><td>Giulia Guizzardi</td><td>Talk</td><td>Executable Research Article (ERA): Enrich a research paper with code and data</td></tr><tr><td>16:00 - 16:15</td><td></td><td></td><td>Break</td></tr><tr><td>16:15 - 16:45</td><td>Fernando Perez</td><td>Talk</td><td>Computing, statistics and reproducibility: pedagogical reflections</td></tr><tr><td>16:45 - 17:15</td><td></td><td>Discussion</td><td>Panel: Reproducible research environments</td></tr><tr><td>17:15 - 18:00</td><td></td><td></td><td>Evaluation &#x26; Networking</td></tr></tbody></table>
<h2 id="abstracts"><a href="#abstracts" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"><span class="icon icon-link"></span></a>Abstracts</h2>
<h3 id="data--code--software--pdf-how-to-write-a-reproducible-research-article"><a href="#data--code--software--pdf-how-to-write-a-reproducible-research-article" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"><span class="icon icon-link"></span></a>Data + Code + Software = PDF: How to write a reproducible research article</h3>
<p><a href="https://twitter.com/adinakrik?lang=en" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Adina Wagner</a></p>
<p>Science is an incremental process that produces and builds up on more than just published journal articles - nevertheless, journals only rarely accept or publish formats other than text documents or PDFs. An alternative to a classic PDF is a reproducible research article, an electronic document that is automatically generated from your project's code, data, and software, and embeds results and figures into the manuscript text as they are computed. With this, reproducible research articles combine adherence to publishers requirements with uncompromising reproducibility, increased reusability, and efficiency.</p>
<p>This talk will be a demonstration of one of many ways to writing an automatically reproducible research article and making it publicly available. It will walk through a traditionally published paper, and reveal the openly available reproducible research article behind it. Beyond this, it will introduce a generic framework to link and share all building blocks of a project, including code, data of any size, software, and the final manuscript.</p>
<h3 id="executable-research-article-era-enrich-a-research-paper-with-code-and-data"><a href="#executable-research-article-era-enrich-a-research-paper-with-code-and-data" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"><span class="icon icon-link"></span></a>Executable Research Article (ERA): Enrich a research paper with code and data</h3>
<p><a href="https://twitter.com/GiuliaGuizza" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Giulia Guizzardi</a></p>
<p>Since 2017, <a href="https://twitter.com/elifeinnovation?lang=en" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">eLife</a> has been working on the concept of computationally reproducible papers. The open-source suite of tools that started life as the Reproducible Document Stack is live since August 2020 on eLife as ERA, the Executable Research Article, delivering a truly web-native format for taking published research to a new level of transparency, reproducibility and interactivity.
At the moment, authors with a published eLife paper can register their interest to enrich their published work with the addition of live code blocks, programmatically-generated interactive figures, and dynamically generated in-line values, using familiar tools like R Markdown and Jupyter in combination with Stencila Hub’s intuitive asset management and format conversion interface. The resulting new ERA publication will be presented as a complement to the original published paper.
Readers of ERA publications are able to inspect the code, modify it, and re-execute it directly in the browser, enabling them to better understand how a figure is generated. They are able to change a plot from one format to another, alter the data range of a specific analysis, and much more. All changes are limited to an individual’s browsing session and do not affect the published article, so anyone can experiment safely. Readers can also download the ERA publication – with all embedded code and data preserved – and use it as a basis for further study or derivative works.</p>
<h3 id="computing-statistics-and-reproducibility-pedagogical-reflections"><a href="#computing-statistics-and-reproducibility-pedagogical-reflections" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"><span class="icon icon-link"></span></a>Computing, statistics and reproducibility: pedagogical reflections</h3>
<p><a href="https://twitter.com/fperez_org?lang=en" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Fernando Perez</a></p>
<p>In this talk Fernando will discuss a course taught in the UC Berkeley statistics department, where they try to combine epistemological reflections on open and reproducible science, statistical considerations for data analysis that leads to robust and trustworthy results, and computational practices that support these ideas.  They use tools from the Scientific Python and Jupyter ecosystem, and try to imbue the students with a practical appreciation of the real-world practice of open, collaborative science by working on open source projects, recently published literature and data.</p>
<p>The main ideas behind this approach can be implemented with other choices of tools as well, so we hope this discussion will be of interest to those who use different tools.</p>
<h2 id="call-for-contributions"><a href="#call-for-contributions" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"><span class="icon icon-link"></span></a>Call for Contributions</h2>
<p>We are always looking for speakers and exciting topics, please contact the host <a href="mailto:c.martinez@esciencecenter.nl">Carlos Martinez</a> if you would like to give a talk or are interested in learning about some specific topics.</p>
<h2 id="contact"><a href="#contact" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"><span class="icon icon-link"></span></a>Contact</h2>
<p>If you have any questions, please contact the host <a href="mailto:c.martinez@esciencecenter.nl">Carlos Martinez</a></p>
            ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[June 11, 2021, NL-RSE Meetup]]></title>
            <link>/events/2021-06-11-meetup</link>
            <guid>June 11, 2021, NL-RSE Meetup</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 18 May 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[
              <p>
                <img
                  alt="Cover image"
                  src="/img/meetup-header-with-logo.jpg"
                >
              </p>
              <p>June 2021 Meetup of the NL-RSE Community.</p>
<!--break-->
<p><img alt="Logo Banner" src="/img/meetups/logo-banner.jpg"></p>
<h2 id="location"><a href="#location" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"><span class="icon icon-link"></span></a>Location</h2>
<p>The call will be conducted with the <a href="https://zoom.us" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">ZOOM</a> conferencing platform. Follow <a href="https://support.zoom.us/hc/en-us/articles/201362193-Joining-a-Meeting" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Joining the Meeting instructions</a>.</p>
<p>Zoom link will be sent to your email with your registration.</p>
<h2 id="registration"><a href="#registration" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"><span class="icon icon-link"></span></a>Registration</h2>
<p>The registration is free.</p>
<p>Please register via this <a href="https://www.eventbrite.co.uk/e/nl-rse-meetup-june-11-2021-tickets-154425768631" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Eventbrite page</a>.</p>
<h2 id="agenda"><a href="#agenda" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"><span class="icon icon-link"></span></a>Agenda</h2>



























































<table><thead><tr><th>Time</th><th>Responsible</th><th>Type</th><th>Subject</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>09:00 - 09:15</td><td></td><td></td><td>hello &#x26; coffee</td></tr><tr><td>09:15 - 09:20</td><td>Carlos Martinez</td><td></td><td>Welcome and purpose</td></tr><tr><td>09:20 - 09:25</td><td>Carlos Martinez</td><td></td><td>Agenda and ground rules</td></tr><tr><td>09:25 - 09:30</td><td>everyone</td><td></td><td>Introductions and announcements</td></tr><tr><td>09:30 - 10:30</td><td>Javier de la Cueva</td><td>Talk</td><td>Open Science and Intellectual Property</td></tr><tr><td>10:45 - 11:15</td><td>Marijn Koolen</td><td>Talk</td><td>Code literacy in Digital Humanities</td></tr><tr><td>11:15 - 11:55</td><td></td><td>discussion</td><td>Parking Lot</td></tr><tr><td>11:55 - 12:00</td><td></td><td>discussion</td><td>Evaluation</td></tr></tbody></table>
<h2 id="abstracts"><a href="#abstracts" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"><span class="icon icon-link"></span></a>Abstracts</h2>
<h3 id="open-science-and-intellectual-property"><a href="#open-science-and-intellectual-property" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"><span class="icon icon-link"></span></a>Open Science and Intellectual Property</h3>
<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Javier_de_la_Cueva" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Javier de la Cueva</a>, who is a European expert in Open Science will share with us his thoughts on the topic.</p>
<h3 id="code-literacy-in-digital-humanities"><a href="#code-literacy-in-digital-humanities" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"><span class="icon icon-link"></span></a>Code literacy in Digital Humanities</h3>
<p>Marijn Koolen recently conducted a survey on code literacy in digital humanities. He will share with us what they found and some insights in what can be done about it.</p>
<h2 id="call-for-contributions"><a href="#call-for-contributions" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"><span class="icon icon-link"></span></a>Call for Contributions</h2>
<p>We are always looking for speakers and exciting topics, please contact the host <a href="mailto:c.martinez@esciencecenter.nl">Carlos Martinez</a> if you would like to give a talk or are interested in learning about some specific topics.</p>
<h2 id="contact"><a href="#contact" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"><span class="icon icon-link"></span></a>Contact</h2>
<p>If you have any questions, please contact the host <a href="mailto:c.martinez@esciencecenter.nl">Carlos Martinez</a></p>
            ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[April 21, 2021, NL-RSE Meetup]]></title>
            <link>/events/2021-04-21-meetup</link>
            <guid>April 21, 2021, NL-RSE Meetup</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 02 Apr 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[
              <p>
                <img
                  alt="Cover image"
                  src="/img/meetup-header-with-logo.jpg"
                >
              </p>
              <p>April 2021 Meetup of the NL-RSE Community.</p>
<!--break-->
<p><img alt="Logo Banner" src="/img/meetups/logo-banner.jpg"></p>
<h2 id="location"><a href="#location" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"><span class="icon icon-link"></span></a>Location</h2>
<p>The call will be conducted with the <a href="https://zoom.us" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">ZOOM</a> conferencing platform. Follow <a href="https://support.zoom.us/hc/en-us/articles/201362193-Joining-a-Meeting" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Joining the Meeting instructions</a>.</p>
<p>Zoom link will be sent to your email with your registration.</p>
<h2 id="registration"><a href="#registration" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"><span class="icon icon-link"></span></a>Registration</h2>
<p>The registration is free.</p>
<p>Please register via this <a href="https://www.eventbrite.co.uk/e/nl-rse-meetup-april-21-2021-tickets-149839202087" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Eventbrite page</a>.</p>
<h2 id="agenda"><a href="#agenda" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"><span class="icon icon-link"></span></a>Agenda</h2>

































































<table><thead><tr><th>Time</th><th>Responsible</th><th>Type</th><th>Subject</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>09:00 - 09:15</td><td></td><td></td><td>hello &#x26; coffee</td></tr><tr><td>09:15 - 09:20</td><td>Carlos Martinez</td><td></td><td>Welcome and purpose</td></tr><tr><td>09:20 - 09:25</td><td>Carlos Martinez</td><td></td><td>Agenda and ground rules</td></tr><tr><td>09:25 - 09:30</td><td>everyone</td><td></td><td>Introductions and announcements</td></tr><tr><td>09:30 - 10:15</td><td>Paul Gerke</td><td>Demo</td><td>The grand-challenge platform for medical imaging</td></tr><tr><td>10:15 - 10:45</td><td>Casper Kaandorp</td><td>Demo</td><td>NIDM (Networking during Infectious Disease Model)</td></tr><tr><td>11:00 - 11:45</td><td>Paul Gerke and Casper Kaandorp</td><td>Panel</td><td>RSE groups</td></tr><tr><td>11:45 - 11:50</td><td></td><td>discussion</td><td>Parking Lot</td></tr><tr><td>11:50 - 12:00</td><td></td><td>discussion</td><td>Evaluation</td></tr></tbody></table>
<h2 id="abstracts"><a href="#abstracts" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"><span class="icon icon-link"></span></a>Abstracts</h2>
<h3 id="the-grand-challenge-platform-for-medical-imaging"><a href="#the-grand-challenge-platform-for-medical-imaging" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"><span class="icon icon-link"></span></a>The grand-challenge platform for medical imaging</h3>
<p>Paul will give an interactive demo of The grand-challenge platform for medical imaging. The demo will highlight the capabilities of the platform as a tool for integrated annotation of medical imaging, with applications for learning &#x26; verification for AI systems.</p>
<h3 id="nidm-networking-during-infectious-disease-model"><a href="#nidm-networking-during-infectious-disease-model" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"><span class="icon icon-link"></span></a>NIDM (Networking during Infectious Disease Model)</h3>
<p>Recent research shows an increasing interest in the interplay of social networks and infectious diseases. Many studies either neglect explicit changes in health behaviour or consider networks to be static, despite empirical evidence that people seek to distance themselves from diseases in social networks. With our application we experiment with a model that integrates theories of social network formation from sociology, risk perception from health psychology, and infectious diseases from epidemiology.</p>
<h3 id="discussion-panel-rse-groups"><a href="#discussion-panel-rse-groups" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"><span class="icon icon-link"></span></a>Discussion panel: RSE groups</h3>
<p>Research Software Engineering groups are increasingly common as part of universities and medical centers. These groups provide support to researchers in developing research software and are key in conducting open and reproducible digital research. In this panel we have invited members of such groups to answer questions about their experiences in conducting research projects in such a context.</p>
<h2 id="call-for-contributions"><a href="#call-for-contributions" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"><span class="icon icon-link"></span></a>Call for Contributions</h2>
<p>We are always looking for speakers and exciting topics, please contact the host <a href="mailto:c.martinez@esciencecenter.nl">Carlos Martinez</a> if you would like to give a talk or are interested in learning about some specific topics.</p>
<h2 id="contact"><a href="#contact" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"><span class="icon icon-link"></span></a>Contact</h2>
<p>If you have any questions, please contact the host <a href="mailto:c.martinez@esciencecenter.nl">Carlos Martinez</a></p>
            ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[February 11, 2021, NL-RSE Meetup]]></title>
            <link>/events/2021-02-11-meetup</link>
            <guid>February 11, 2021, NL-RSE Meetup</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 26 Jan 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[
              <p>
                <img
                  alt="Cover image"
                  src="/img/meetup-header-with-logo.jpg"
                >
              </p>
              <p>February 2021 Meetup of the NL-RSE Community.</p>
<!--break-->
<p><img alt="Logo Banner" src="/img/meetups/logo-banner.jpg"></p>
<h2 id="location"><a href="#location" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"><span class="icon icon-link"></span></a>Location</h2>
<p>The call will be conducted with the <a href="https://zoom.us" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">ZOOM</a> conferencing platform. Follow <a href="https://support.zoom.us/hc/en-us/articles/201362193-Joining-a-Meeting" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Joining the Meeting instructions</a>.</p>
<p>Zoom link will be sent to your email with your registration.</p>
<h2 id="registration"><a href="#registration" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"><span class="icon icon-link"></span></a>Registration</h2>
<p>The registration is free.</p>
<p>Please register via this <a href="https://www.eventbrite.co.uk/e/nl-rse-meetup-february-11-2021-tickets-138243358607" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Eventbrite page</a>.</p>
<h2 id="agenda"><a href="#agenda" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"><span class="icon icon-link"></span></a>Agenda</h2>













































































<table><thead><tr><th>Time</th><th>Responsible</th><th>Type</th><th>Subject</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>09:00 - 09:15</td><td></td><td></td><td>hello &#x26; coffee</td></tr><tr><td>09:15 - 09:20</td><td>Carlos Martinez</td><td></td><td>Welcome and purpose</td></tr><tr><td>09:20 - 09:25</td><td>Carlos Martinez</td><td></td><td>Agenda and ground rules</td></tr><tr><td>09:25 - 09:30</td><td>everyone</td><td></td><td>Introductions and announcements</td></tr><tr><td>09:30 - 10:00</td><td>Stephanie Holst</td><td>Presentation</td><td>NWO Open Science Funds</td></tr><tr><td>10:00 - 10:30</td><td>Margriet Miedema</td><td>Presentation</td><td>What do DCC's mean for RSEs?</td></tr><tr><td>10:30 - 10:45</td><td></td><td></td><td>break</td></tr><tr><td>10:45 - 11:30</td><td>Faruk Diblen</td><td>Discussion</td><td>Software re-usability -- what is needed?</td></tr><tr><td>11:30 - 11:35</td><td></td><td>discussion</td><td>Parking Lot</td></tr><tr><td>11:35 - 11:40</td><td></td><td>discussion</td><td>Evaluation</td></tr><tr><td>11:40 - ??:??</td><td>everyone</td><td>open</td><td>Networking moment</td></tr></tbody></table>
<h2 id="abstracts"><a href="#abstracts" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"><span class="icon icon-link"></span></a>Abstracts</h2>
<h3 id="nwo-open-science-fund"><a href="#nwo-open-science-fund" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"><span class="icon icon-link"></span></a>NWO Open Science Fund</h3>
<p>Stephanie Holst, Programme officer at NWO, will talk about the <a href="https://www.nwo.nl/en/calls/open-science-fund-2020/2021" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Open Science Fund</a>. With this call, NWO wants to stimulate the broader adoption and implementation of Open Science by incentivizing and rewarding Open Science practices. This call aims to support researchers making research open, accessible, transparent and reusable – this includes research software developed for Open Science. This call could be of interest to Research Software Engineers already using Open Science practices! Stephanie will provide more information on who can apply, what to apply for and other details of this call.</p>
<h3 id="what-do-dccs-mean-for-rses"><a href="#what-do-dccs-mean-for-rses" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"><span class="icon icon-link"></span></a>What do DCC's mean for RSEs?</h3>
<p>Margriet Miedema from <a href="https://www.lcrdm.nl/en" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">LCRDM</a> will talk about the Digital Competence Centres Implementation Network. What are DCCs, why are they important for RSEs? With this talk we would like to open up a conversation and communicate with DCCs what are the challenges RSEs face and how can we work together with DCCs to find solutions to those issues.</p>
<h3 id="software-re-usability----what-is-needed"><a href="#software-re-usability----what-is-needed" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"><span class="icon icon-link"></span></a>Software re-usability -- what is needed?</h3>
<p>Reusability is a critical point for research software -- it is generally seen as a sign of success when a particular piece of software is reused by many users. But this is not always easy, users who come across your software may not always know what it is capable of, or find it difficult to understand how to use it.</p>
<p>There is a already a large collection of checklists that can be used to make sure your software meets certain quality criteria. In this session we would like to discuss: how do RSEs make sure their software is reusable?</p>
<h2 id="call-for-contributions"><a href="#call-for-contributions" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"><span class="icon icon-link"></span></a>Call for Contributions</h2>
<p>We are always looking for speakers and exciting topics, please contact the host <a href="mailto:c.martinez@esciencecenter.nl">Carlos Martinez</a> if you would like to give a talk or are interested in learning about some specific topics.</p>
<h2 id="contact"><a href="#contact" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"><span class="icon icon-link"></span></a>Contact</h2>
<p>If you have any questions, please contact the host <a href="mailto:c.martinez@esciencecenter.nl">Carlos Martinez</a></p>
            ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[December 16, 2020, NL-RSE Meetup]]></title>
            <link>/events/2020-12-16-meetup</link>
            <guid>December 16, 2020, NL-RSE Meetup</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 01 Nov 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[
              <p>
                <img
                  alt="Cover image"
                  src="/img/meetup-header-with-logo.jpg"
                >
              </p>
              <p>December 2020 Meetup of the NL-RSE Community.</p>
<!--break-->
<p><img alt="Logo Banner" src="/img/meetups/logo-banner.jpg"></p>
<h2 id="location"><a href="#location" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"><span class="icon icon-link"></span></a>Location</h2>
<p>The call will be conducted with the <a href="https://zoom.us" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">ZOOM</a> conferencing platform. Follow <a href="https://support.zoom.us/hc/en-us/articles/201362193-Joining-a-Meeting" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Joining the Meeting instructions</a>.</p>
<p>Zoom link will be published soon.</p>
<h2 id="registration"><a href="#registration" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"><span class="icon icon-link"></span></a>Registration</h2>
<p>The registration is free<br></p>
<p>Please register via this <a href="https://www.eventbrite.co.uk/e/nl-rse-meetup-december-16-2020-tickets-129300434079" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Eventbrite page</a>.</p>
<h2 id="agenda"><a href="#agenda" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"><span class="icon icon-link"></span></a>Agenda</h2>





















































<table><thead><tr><th>Time</th><th>Responsible</th><th>Type</th><th>Subject</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>09:00 - 09:15</td><td></td><td></td><td>hello &#x26; coffee</td></tr><tr><td>09:15 - 09:20</td><td>Mateusz Kuzak</td><td></td><td>Welcome and purpose</td></tr><tr><td>09:20 - 09:25</td><td>Mateusz Kuzak</td><td></td><td>Agenda and ground rules</td></tr><tr><td>09:25 - 09:30</td><td>everyone</td><td></td><td>Introductions and announcements</td></tr><tr><td>09:30 - 12:30</td><td>Mattia Mancini</td><td>tutorial</td><td>From a bash script to CWL</td></tr><tr><td>12:30 - 12:35</td><td></td><td>discussion</td><td>Parking Lot</td></tr><tr><td>12:35 - 12:40</td><td></td><td>discussion</td><td>Evaluation</td></tr></tbody></table>
<h2 id="abstracts"><a href="#abstracts" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"><span class="icon icon-link"></span></a>Abstracts</h2>
<h3 id="from-a-bash-script-to-cwl"><a href="#from-a-bash-script-to-cwl" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"><span class="icon icon-link"></span></a>From a bash script to CWL</h3>
<p>In modern experimental sciences, the increasing amount of data to process and the development of standardized procedures to analyze it, is driving the utilization of automatic processing pipelines.
Such pipelines combine different software components to carry out the computation.
A wide range of solutions, ranging from bash scripts to python, can be used to perform such orchestration.</p>
<p>In ASTRON for the European Open Science Cloud project, we chose to use the Common Workflow Language (CWL) to describe one of our standard processing pipelines.</p>
<p>In this demo and tutorial, we will show our experience in converting our pipeline into the CWL (v1.0) standard and our experience with the available tools to run it and visualize it. We will follow by showing you how to create a CWL step and a CWL pipeline to describe an example workflow. Finally, we will conclude the meeting with our take on why we choose CWL and why this proved to be fit to solve our problems, and we would be welcome your opinions about that.</p>
<p><strong>Our use case comes from astronomy, but this tutorial is focused on transferable skills which can be applied in other domains.</strong></p>
<p>For the tutorial, we will be using <a href="https://colab.research.google.com" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">google colab</a>
please make sure that you can execute it in your browser.</p>
<p>If you want to run the software on your computer, you will require the following tools installed on your laptop:</p>
<ul>
<li>Python 3.6 (or higher)</li>
<li>cwltool (to execute the workflow) - we recommend to use it in a virtual environment (<a href="https://github.com/common-workflow-language/cwltool" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">here</a> is a guide on how to install it)</li>
<li>singularity/docker (in case of the software we use in the demo is not available for your system,</li>
</ul>
<p>here are install instructions for <a href="https://sylabs.io/guides/3.0/user-guide/installation.html" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">singularity</a> and <a href="https://docs.docker.com/get-docker/" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">docker</a>) -- if you are not running linux/mac we strongly suggest using google colab!</p>
<p>As there is not much time during the tutorial, we suggest that, if you want to run the software on your computer, you make sure that you can <a href="https://www.commonwl.org/user_guide/02-1st-example/index.html" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">run this example</a> and docker or singularity is available.</p>
<h2 id="call-for-contributions"><a href="#call-for-contributions" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"><span class="icon icon-link"></span></a>Call for Contributions</h2>
<p>We are always looking for speakers and exciting topics, please contact the host <a href="mailto:m.kuzak@esciencecenter.nl">Mateusz Kuzak</a> if you would like to give a talk or are interested in learning about some specific topics.</p>
<h2 id="contact"><a href="#contact" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"><span class="icon icon-link"></span></a>Contact</h2>
<p>If you have any questions, please contact the host <a href="mailto:m.kuzak@esciencecenter.nl">Mateusz Kuzak</a></p>
            ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[November 20, 2020, NL-RSE Meetup]]></title>
            <link>/events/2020-11-20-meetup</link>
            <guid>November 20, 2020, NL-RSE Meetup</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 05 Oct 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[
              <p>
                <img
                  alt="Cover image"
                  src="/img/meetup-header-with-logo.jpg"
                >
              </p>
              <p>November 2020 Online meetup of the NL-RSE Community.</p>
<!--break-->
<p><img alt="Logo Banner" src="/img/meetups/logo-banner.jpg"></p>
<h2 id="location"><a href="#location" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"><span class="icon icon-link"></span></a>Location</h2>
<p>The call will be conducted with the <a href="https://zoom.us" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">ZOOM</a> conferencing platform. Follow <a href="https://support.zoom.us/hc/en-us/articles/201362193-Joining-a-Meeting" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Joining the Meeting instructions</a>.</p>
<p>Zoom link will be published soon.</p>
<h2 id="registration"><a href="#registration" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"><span class="icon icon-link"></span></a>Registration</h2>
<p>The registration is free<br></p>
<p>Please register via this <a href="https://www.eventbrite.co.uk/e/nl-rse-meetup-november-20-2020-tickets-126405926529" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Eventbrite page</a>.</p>
<h2 id="agenda"><a href="#agenda" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"><span class="icon icon-link"></span></a>Agenda</h2>







































































<table><thead><tr><th>Time</th><th>Responsible</th><th>Type</th><th>Subject</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>09:00 - 09:15</td><td></td><td></td><td>hello &#x26; coffee</td></tr><tr><td>09:15 - 09:20</td><td>Mateusz Kuzak</td><td></td><td>Welcome and purpose</td></tr><tr><td>09:20 - 09:25</td><td>Mateusz Kuzak</td><td></td><td>Agenda and ground rules</td></tr><tr><td>09:25 - 09:30</td><td>everyone</td><td></td><td>Introductions and announcements</td></tr><tr><td>09:30 - 11:00</td><td>Richard Zijdeman</td><td>interactive session</td><td>Grlc + RAMOSE</td></tr><tr><td>11:00 - 11:15</td><td></td><td>break</td><td></td></tr><tr><td>11:15 - 11:45</td><td>Meiert Grootes</td><td>talk + demo</td><td>Evidence</td></tr><tr><td>11:45 - 12:45</td><td>Jaap Blom</td><td>talk + demo</td><td>Annotation tools</td></tr><tr><td>12:45 - 12:50</td><td></td><td>discussion</td><td>Parking Lot</td></tr><tr><td>12:50 - 12:55</td><td></td><td>discussion</td><td>Evaluation</td></tr></tbody></table>
<h2 id="abstracts"><a href="#abstracts" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"><span class="icon icon-link"></span></a>Abstracts</h2>
<h2 id="grlc--ramose-user-meeting----how-do-you-apply-grlc-what-could-be-better-whats-really-bad"><a href="#grlc--ramose-user-meeting----how-do-you-apply-grlc-what-could-be-better-whats-really-bad" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"><span class="icon icon-link"></span></a>Grlc + RAMOSE user meeting -- how do you apply grlc, what could be better, what's really bad?</h2>
<p><a href="https://github.com/CLARIAH/grlc" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">grlc</a> is a lightweight server that creates Web APIs to access Linked Data. SPARQL queries are transformed into API endpoints. API parameters can be mapped to query variables, adding flexibility to how the data is accessed.</p>
<p>Grlc has been successfully used in a number of projects, but it is far from perfect. In this session we would like to have a discussion with grlc users (and potential users) to discuss what are the current limitations and points of improvement.</p>
<p>RAMOSE[<a href="https://github.com/opencitations/ramose" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">https://github.com/opencitations/ramose</a>] (Restful API Manager Over SPARQL Endpoints) is an application that allows agile development and publication of RESTful APIs for querying SPARQL endpoints according to a markdown-alike specification document.</p>
<p>RAMOSE is currently used by the <a href="http://opencitations.net/" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">OpenCitations</a> infrastructure to serve several RDF datasets to non-semantic web developers. In this presentation a few motivations for developing (yet another) API on SPARQL endpoints will be introduced, so as to support the discussion on grlc roadmap based on similar experiences.</p>
<p>The outcome of this session will be the grlc roadmap -- a list of Github issues that the grlc developers (and potential contributors) can use to further develop grlc!</p>
<h2 id="evidence----a-machine-assisted-close-reading-tool-with-support-for-abstract-concept-based-search-and-context-based-search"><a href="#evidence----a-machine-assisted-close-reading-tool-with-support-for-abstract-concept-based-search-and-context-based-search" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"><span class="icon icon-link"></span></a>Evidence -- a machine assisted close reading tool with support for abstract concept-based search and context-based search.</h2>
<p>Digitization of text corpora has benefited humanities research by simplifying access and enabling the use of text analysis tools. However, the standard entry point used by current systems is keyword based search - an entry point incompatible with proven methods of scholarly close reading. Close reading is a key element in the pursuit of research questions focussing on complex or abstract concepts. In these situations keyword search based entry point often proves to be very restrictive, making it difficult, if not impossible, to formulate adequate search criteria and queries. Here we present a machine assisted close reading tool called <a href="https://research-software.nl/software/evidence" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Evidence</a>. It provides an alternative, intuitive entry point into collections.</p>
<p>Evidence uses machine learning to extract a vector-space representation of the theme and content of all corpus elements. Using Evidence, users can query the corpus starting from elements embodying their research question. We call this concept-based querying. Additionally, Evidence allows classical word-based querying. This enables the user to search a large, digitised corpus with a focus on complex or abstract research questions. In this way Evidence assists the user's close reading.</p>
<p>This presentation provides the audience with the relevant background and shows what Evidence is capable of.</p>
<h2 id="architecture-and-underlying-principles-of-the-clariah-media-suite-annotation-tools"><a href="#architecture-and-underlying-principles-of-the-clariah-media-suite-annotation-tools" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"><span class="icon icon-link"></span></a>Architecture and underlying principles of the CLARIAH Media Suite annotation tools</h2>
<h3 id="how-open-standards-improve-the-publication--exchange-of-your-annotation-data"><a href="#how-open-standards-improve-the-publication--exchange-of-your-annotation-data" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"><span class="icon icon-link"></span></a>How open standards improve the publication &#x26; exchange of (your) annotation data.</h3>
<p>The <a href="https://mediasuite.clariah.nl/" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">CLARIAH Media Suite</a> serves media scholars and other (digital) humanities scholars by providing access to several (Dutch) audiovisual collections, such as television &#x26; radio programmes, films, newspapers and oral history interviews. The Media Suite annotation tools allow users to add and share personal annotations to specific audiovisual resources, for example over a determined area on an image or at a specific time in a video. This talk details about the architecture and underlying principles of the Media Suite annotation tools and how open standards improve the publication &#x26; exchange of (your) annotation data.</p>
<h2 id="call-for-contributions"><a href="#call-for-contributions" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"><span class="icon icon-link"></span></a>Call for Contributions</h2>
<p>We are always looking for speakers and exciting topics, please contact the host <a href="mailto:m.kuzak@esciencecenter.nl">Mateusz Kuzak</a> if you would like to give a talk or are interested in learning about some specific topics.</p>
<h2 id="contact"><a href="#contact" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"><span class="icon icon-link"></span></a>Contact</h2>
<p>If you have any questions, please contact the host <a href="mailto:m.kuzak@esciencecenter.nl">Mateusz Kuzak</a></p>
            ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[March 13, 2020, NL-RSE Meetup]]></title>
            <link>/events/2020-03-13-meetup</link>
            <guid>March 13, 2020, NL-RSE Meetup</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[
              <p>
                <img
                  alt="Cover image"
                  src="/img/meetup-header-with-logo.jpg"
                >
              </p>
              <p>March 2020 Meetup of the NL-RSE Community.</p>
<!--break-->
<p><img alt="Logo Banner" src="/img/meetups/logo-banner.jpg"></p>
<h2 id="location"><a href="#location" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"><span class="icon icon-link"></span></a>Location</h2>
<p>Out of concern about your health and the spread of the COVID-19, and as a response to the travel and meeting restrictions emerging within the Netherlands and around the world, the NL-RSE Core Team decided to make this Friday’s meetup fully online.</p>
<p>The call will be conducted with the <a href="https://zoom.us" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">ZOOM</a> conferencing platform. Please make sure to install and test it before Friday. Follow <a href="https://support.zoom.us/hc/en-us/articles/201362193-Joining-a-Meeting" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Joining the Meeting instructions</a>.</p>
<p>Connect with this <a href="https://us04web.zoom.us/j/5150701241" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Zoom link</a></p>
<h2 id="registration"><a href="#registration" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"><span class="icon icon-link"></span></a>Registration</h2>
<p>The registration is free and includes lunch and drinks.<br>
Please register via this <a href="https://www.eventbrite.co.uk/e/nl-rse-meetup-march-13-2020-tickets-90593053261#" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Eventbrite page</a>.</p>
<h2 id="agenda"><a href="#agenda" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"><span class="icon icon-link"></span></a>Agenda</h2>
<p><a href="https://tinyurl.com/2020-03-13-nl-rse" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Collaborative Document &#x26; Agenda</a></p>

























































































<table><thead><tr><th>Time</th><th>Responsible</th><th>Type</th><th>Subject</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>10:30 - 11:00</td><td></td><td></td><td>hello &#x26; coffee</td></tr><tr><td>11:00 - 11:05</td><td>Mateusz Kuzak</td><td></td><td>Welcome and purpose</td></tr><tr><td>11:05 - 11:10</td><td>Mateusz Kuzak</td><td></td><td>Agenda and ground rules</td></tr><tr><td>11:10 - 11:30</td><td>everyone</td><td></td><td>Introductions and announcements</td></tr><tr><td>11:30 - 12:00</td><td>Gijs Molenaar</td><td>talk</td><td>"Training a reinforcement agent with simulations of the Dutch electricity Grid to optimize long-term investment strategies" <a href="http://pythonic.nl" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">http://pythonic.nl</a></td></tr><tr><td>12:00 - 12:30</td><td>Emmy Tsang</td><td>talk</td><td>"Community driven solutions for better research communication", <a href="https://elifesciences.org/labs" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">eLife Innovation</a></td></tr><tr><td>12:30 - 12:45</td><td>anyone</td><td>talk</td><td>Lightning Talks</td></tr><tr><td>12:45 - 13:30</td><td></td><td></td><td>Lunch break</td></tr><tr><td>13:30 - 14:20</td><td>Felipe Zapata</td><td>hands-on</td><td>"Continuous integration and Continuous Delivery for scientific applications" <a href="https://github.com/NLESC-JCER/ci_for_science" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">ci for science</a></td></tr><tr><td>14:20 - 14:30</td><td></td><td></td><td>Tea break</td></tr><tr><td>14:30 - 15:20</td><td>everyone, facilitators: Emmy Tsang, Hakim Achterberg</td><td>collaborative session</td><td>What makes good documentation?</td></tr><tr><td>15:20 - 15:25</td><td></td><td>discussion</td><td>Parking Lot</td></tr><tr><td>15:25 - 15:30</td><td></td><td>discussion</td><td>Evaluation</td></tr></tbody></table>
<h2 id="abstracts"><a href="#abstracts" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"><span class="icon icon-link"></span></a>Abstracts</h2>
<h3 id="gijs-molenaar-training-a-reinforcement-agent-with-simulations-of-the-dutch-electricity-grid-to-optimize-long-term-investment-strategies"><a href="#gijs-molenaar-training-a-reinforcement-agent-with-simulations-of-the-dutch-electricity-grid-to-optimize-long-term-investment-strategies" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"><span class="icon icon-link"></span></a>Gijs Molenaar "Training a reinforcement agent with simulations of the Dutch electricity Grid to optimize long-term investment strategies"</h3>
<p>As a free-lance research engineer, I'm currently involved in creating a simulation of the Dutch electricity grid maintained by Alliander. These simulations run 40 years in the future, repeated numerous times each with a different set of random growth conditions. The outputs of these simulations are used to train a deep reinforcement agent the optimise long-term investment strategies of the company.</p>
<p>In this talk, I will talk about the tools and techniques used (Python, NumPy, Kubernetes, Neo4j), our development infrastructure and our team's work distribution.</p>
<h3 id="emmy-tsang-community-driven-solutions-for-better-research-communication"><a href="#emmy-tsang-community-driven-solutions-for-better-research-communication" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"><span class="icon icon-link"></span></a>Emmy Tsang "Community driven solutions for better research communication"</h3>
<p>The advancement of web technologies has created an opportunity for developing tools for real-time collaborations, text-mining, interactive data visualisations, sharing reproducible compute environments, etc. These tools can change the ways researchers share, discover, consume and evaluate research and help promote open science and encourage responsible research behaviours. Through its Innovation Initiative, eLife invests heavily in software development, new product design, collaboration and outreach so that the potential for improvements in the digital communication of new research can start to be realised. In this talk, I hope to share some of the tools and projects we've been supporting and creating and hope to invite feedback and contributions from the NL-RSE community on the next steps forward.</p>
<h3 id="felipe-zapata-continuous-integration-and-continuous-delivery-for-scientific-applications"><a href="#felipe-zapata-continuous-integration-and-continuous-delivery-for-scientific-applications" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"><span class="icon icon-link"></span></a>Felipe Zapata "Continuous integration and Continuous Delivery for scientific applications"</h3>
<p>Continuous integration is the practice of integrating code changes into a software project in an automated way.
In this hands-on session, we will explore how to create pipelines to automate the process of building and
testing scientific software, using open source tools like GitHub actions, GitlabCI and Travis.</p>
<h2 id="call-for-contributions"><a href="#call-for-contributions" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"><span class="icon icon-link"></span></a>Call for Contributions</h2>
<p>We are always looking for speakers and exciting topics, please contact the host <a href="mailto:m.kuzak@esciencecenter.nl">Mateusz Kuzak</a> if you would like to give a talk or are interested in learning about some specific topics.</p>
<h2 id="contact"><a href="#contact" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"><span class="icon icon-link"></span></a>Contact</h2>
<p>If you have any questions, please contact the host <a href="mailto:m.kuzak@esciencecenter.nl">Mateusz Kuzak</a></p>
            ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[NL-RSE19]]></title>
            <link>/events/NL-RSE19</link>
            <guid>NL-RSE19</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 20 Nov 2019 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[
              <p>
                <img
                  alt="Cover image"
                  src="/img/conference-banner-flatv2.jpg"
                >
              </p>
              <p>NL-RSE is organizing the NL-RSE19 conference on November 20 at the Johan Cruijff ArenA, Amsterdam.</p>
<!--break-->
<p><strong>When: 20 November 2019</strong></p>
<p><strong>Where: <a href="https://www.johancruijffarena.nl/" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Johan Cruijff ArenA</a> in Amsterdam</strong></p>
<p><strong>Registration: Closed</strong></p>
<p>At NL-RSE19, we will bring together the Research Software Engineers (RSE) community to talk about, building the community, best practices for creating research software, and other RSE related
topics. The conference will take place on the 20th of November, at the Johan Cruijff ArenA, Amsterdam.</p>
<p>NL-RSE19 is co-located with the <a href="https://www.esciencesymposium2019.nl/" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">National eScience Symposium 2019</a> taking place the following day, and we greatly appreciate the Netherlands eScience Center
for sponsoring the venue.</p>
<p>The increasing use of data and digital technology in academia has gone hand in hand with a strong growth in people who write and contribute to research software. Positions like data steward,
information manager, research data officer, research software engineer, research supporter and other titles are increasingly recognized as intrinsic positions in the academic system.</p>
<p>Following the great initiatives in the UK and Germany, we plan to bring together the community of people writing and contributing to research software from Dutch universities, knowledge
institutes, companies and other organizations to share knowledge, to organize meetings, and raise awareness for the scientific recognition of research software.</p>
<h2 id="who-should-attend"><a href="#who-should-attend" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"><span class="icon icon-link"></span></a>Who should attend?</h2>
<ul>
<li>Researchers who develop software for research purposes</li>
<li>Software developers working in a research context</li>
<li>People from any organisation providing services to facilitate research software: tools makers, infrastructure providers, computing services, data centers, etc.</li>
<li>Anyone with a stake in research software (funders, publishers, decision makers, etc).</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="program"><a href="#program" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"><span class="icon icon-link"></span></a>Program</h2>
<p>(links to slides)</p>
















































































<table><thead><tr><th>Time</th><th>Madrid 69</th><th>Belgrado 73</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>9:00 - 9:45</td><td>-</td><td>Welcome with coffee</td></tr><tr><td>9:45 - 10:00</td><td>-</td><td><a href="/resources/20191120/nlrse19-drost.pdf">NL-RSE19 Opening</a></td></tr><tr><td>10:00 - 10:30</td><td>-</td><td><em>Keynote talk</em>: <strong><a href="/resources/20191120/nlrse19-allard.pdf">IMPLICIT NONE: intentional inclusion and diversity in the RSE movement</a></strong> -- Tania Allard</td></tr><tr><td>10:30 - 11:10</td><td><strong><a href="/resources/20191120/nlrse19-merono.pdf">For We Are Many: The DHTech White Paper on Research Software Engineering for Digital Humanities</a></strong> - Albert Meroño-Peñuela</td><td><strong><a href="/resources/20191120/nlrse19-aruni.pdf">Functional package management using Guix</a></strong> -- I, Arun</td></tr><tr><td></td><td><strong><a href="/resources/20191120/nlrse19-woodbridge-cohen.pdf">Strength in Numbers: Growing RSE Capacity at Imperial College London</a></strong> - Mark Woodbridge and Jeremy Cohen</td><td><strong><a href="/resources/20191120/nlrse19-grange.pdf">The ASTRON Science Data Centre</a></strong> -- Yan Grange</td></tr><tr><td>11:10 - 11:30</td><td>Coffee break <strong>(Plein van 100)</strong></td><td></td></tr><tr><td>11:30 - 12:30</td><td><strong>Collecting historical tweets</strong> - Martine de Vos</td><td><strong><a href="/resources/20191120/nlrse19-philips.pdf">Workflow automation using Docker Swarm and GitLab CI at Flanders Institute for Biomechanical Experimentation</a></strong> -- Johan Philips</td></tr><tr><td></td><td><strong><a href="/resources/20191120/nlrse19-chourdakis.pdf">Creating a community of contributors for scientific open-source projects: The preCICE case</a></strong> - Gerasimos Chourdakis</td><td><strong><a href="/resources/20191120/nlrse19-hidding.pdf">Literate programming, why it matters and how to make it easy</a></strong> -- Johan Hidding</td></tr><tr><td></td><td><strong><a href="/resources/20191120/nlrse19-sufi.pdf">Highlights from the Workshop on Sustainable Software Sustainability</a></strong> - Shoaib Sufi</td><td><strong><a href="/resources/20191120/nlrse19-maassen-kuzniar.pdf">Xenon introduction &#x26; highly portable parallel [genomics] workflows based on Snakemake/Xenon</a></strong> -- Jason Maassen</td></tr><tr><td>12:30 - 13:30</td><td>Lunch break <strong>(Tokio 95)</strong></td><td></td></tr><tr><td>13:30 - 14:30</td><td><strong>Raising the Profile of Research Software: community feedback session</strong> - Nicolas Renaud</td><td><strong>Introduction to Research Cloud</strong> -- Martin Brandt</td></tr><tr><td>14:30 - 15:00</td><td>Coffee break <strong>(Tokio 95)</strong></td><td></td></tr><tr><td>15:00 - 16:00</td><td><strong>Five recommendations for FAIR software</strong> - Jurriaan Spaaks</td><td><strong>CI/CD for reproducible research</strong> -- Tania Allard</td></tr><tr><td>16:00 - 17:30</td><td>Drinks and Posters <strong>(Tokio 95)</strong></td><td></td></tr></tbody></table>
<h2 id="registration"><a href="#registration" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"><span class="icon icon-link"></span></a>Registration</h2>
<p>Please <a href="https://21pryvp.momice.events/" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">click here</a> for the registration pages.
The registration fee for NL-RSE19 will be EUR 25. Requests for a waiver of this fee are possible, please contact <a href="mailto:info@nl-rse.org">info@nl-rse.org</a>.</p>
<h2 id="call-for-contributions"><a href="#call-for-contributions" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"><span class="icon icon-link"></span></a>Call for Contributions</h2>
<p>The call for contributions is <del>open until September 20</del> <strong>extended until September 27</strong>! We hope to provide an inspiring program, and welcome talks, posters, and workshops on both technical
and other topics related to Research Software Engineers. We very much welcome first time presenters. <a href="https://nl-rse.org/2019/07/09/NL-RSE-2019.html" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Read more</a>.</p>
<h2 id="contact"><a href="#contact" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"><span class="icon icon-link"></span></a>Contact</h2>
<p>If you have any questions, please contact us at <a href="mailto:conference@nl-rse.org">conference@nl-rse.org</a></p>
<h2 id="escience-symposium"><a href="#escience-symposium" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"><span class="icon icon-link"></span></a>eScience Symposium</h2>
<p>NL-RSE19 is co-located with the <a href="https://www.esciencesymposium2019.nl/" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">National eScience Symposium 2019</a> taking place the following day, and we greatly
appreciate the <a href="https://www.esciencecenter.nl/" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Netherlands eScience Center</a> for sponsoring the venue.</p>
            ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>